<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest and cleer ansvver to Mr. Ball's discourse of set formes of prayer. Written by the reverend and learned John Cotton, B.D. and teacher of the Church of Christ at Boston in New-England. Published for the benefit of those who desire satisfaction in that point</title>
            <author>Cotton, John, 1584-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212884</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895587</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895587</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2350:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest and cleer ansvver to Mr. Ball's discourse of set formes of prayer. Written by the reverend and learned John Cotton, B.D. and teacher of the Church of Christ at Boston in New-England. Published for the benefit of those who desire satisfaction in that point</title>
                  <author>Cotton, John, 1584-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Overton in Popes-Head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1642?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Ball, John.  A friendly triall of the grounds tending to separation.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Advertisements upon the discourse of set forms of prayer.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ball, John, 1585-1640. --  Friendly triall of the grounds tending to separation --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:1"/>
            <p>A MODEST AND Cleer Anſvver TO Mr. <hi>Ball's</hi> Diſcourſe OF Set Formes OF PRAYER. Written by the Reverend and Learned <hi>John Cotton,</hi> B. D. and Teacher of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> Publiſhed for the Benefit of thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſatisfaction in that Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Overton</hi> in <hi>Popes-Head</hi> Alley.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:2"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E think it not meet, to fall a commending the <hi>Author</hi> of this work, who hath been ſo long precious in the hearts of all the Saints, and for his learning, pains and piety ſo famous in the Churches of Chriſt; that his own Works may praiſe him in the Gate, though we be ſilent. Neither ſhall we need (as uſually men do in their Epiſtles) to ſet gloſſes upon the work, thy ſelf (if thou weigheſt it with a ſerious and impartial ſpirit) we believe, will do it, and ſave us that labour. This only we ſay, thou wilt diſcern (as ſome other godly learned, who have peruſed it before alſo have done) ſuch a cleer judgement, dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:153145:3"/>aptneſs, and pithy plainneſſe in a moderate and brotherly ſtile in all his Anſwers, that thou wilt think thou ſeeſt the very ſpirit of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> breathing in every page and line. Now, the Father of lights clear all our minds, that if his bleſſed will ſo be, we may think and judge, and ſpeak and write the ſame thing; And the God of all Grace warm our hearts with a love of ſuch truths as we doe know, that we may walk in the light and power thereof, to the praiſe of his Grace, till we all meet in one, and ſee him as he is, and ſo be filled with all the fulneſſe of God himſelf for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153145:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS UPON The Diſcourſe of ſet-forms of PRAYER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Preface touching the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and nature of prayer, I inſiſt not upon; as not much material to the cleering of the Cauſe in hand: it is enough in this Caſe, to premiſe what prayer in Generall is, and what is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayer: Prayer (in generall, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending both lawfull and unlawfull) is the lifting up (or powring out) of the Deſires of the heart for Divine bleſſings; Divine I ſay, that is, for ſuch as God only can give, either for the nature, or kind of the thing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or for the manner of giving.</p>
            <p>Lawfull prayer, is a lifting up (or powring out) of the deſires of the heart unto God, for Divine bleſſings, according to his will in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153145:4"/>name of Jeſus Christ, by the help of the <hi>Spirit of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The State of the Queſtion.</head>
               <p>FOr ſtating of the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> you give ſix Rules, of which I will only touch ſo many, as do more neerly touch upon the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In your firſt Rule you ſay, it is not a Prayer, as penned, or printed, but as rehearſed, with underſtanding, feeling of wants, humility, confidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nor is it a prayer as rehearſed, though rehearſed with underſtanding, feeling of wants, humility, confidence, unleſſe a man therein powre out his <hi>own deſires</hi> unto God; for I may read and rehearſe a printed Prayer (ſay one of <hi>Davids</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall prayers againſt the enemies of the Church) yea, I may read it with underſtanding, with feeling of the wants of ſuch a mercy, and alſo with humility, (in conſcience of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches unworthineſſe of ſuch a mercy, and with confidence that God will do for the Church now, as <hi>David</hi> prayed then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet this will not be my prayer, unleſſe I put up mine own deſires in it: but about this there is no queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Though it be not a prayer, as penned or printed, yet is a means, and help and form of prayer, which either muſt find a warrant from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153145:4"/>the Word, or fall under the breach of the ſecond Commandement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſecond Rule you ſay, the controverſie is not of this or that preſcript form of Prayer in particular, much leſſe of one for ſubſtance of matter, faulty and erronious: But of a preſcript form of prayer in generall, whether it be lawfull to uſe any ſet form of prayer at all, though for the matter thereof never ſo ſound and allowable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But ſo to put the State of the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> is indeed, to leade your ſelf and others into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for if it may be once obtained: that ſome preſcript form is lawfull in the Generall, this in the Theory will ſtraight be reduced to this practice, to perſwade men to joyn in ſuch a preſcript form of prayer as is juſtly liable to manifold exceptions, both for matter and manner.</p>
               <p>If ſuch as were compelled to worſhip the Lord before the golden Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> ſhould put the ſtate of the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> not of ſuch particular Calves, but of Calves, or Cherubims in generall (for one form of Cherubims were like Calves) whether it be not lawfull to worſhip the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Cherubims at all? It may be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, what the iſſue would be, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the lawfulneſſe of ſome Cherubims in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (which is out of queſtion.) The practice will conclude the lawfulneſſe of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves in particular; which was the ſin which made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Your fift Rule acknowledgeth that neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, preſcribed any ſet form of prayer, and therefore that no preſcript form of prayer of Lyturgie is ſimply neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153145:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But this argueth not only no neceſſity of preſcript forms, but alſo no expediency thereof to the edification of the Church, unleſſe it might be preſumed that there is ſome help or means of Gods worſhip expedient to the edification of the Church, which never came into the heart of Chriſt and of his Apoſtles to commend unto the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In your ſixt Rule you profeſſe, you never held it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to tye any mans ſelfe, or to be tyed alwayes to a ſet form of Prayer: as knowing that our requeſts are to be framed according to the preſent neceſſity and occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But by the ſame reaſon, neither will it be lawfull to be tyed at any time to an ordinary uſe of any ſet form of prayer at all: for there is no change of time wherein the Church hath not ſome ſpeciall occaſion to change their <hi>Petitions,</hi> either by adding ſome <hi>Petitions</hi> more than formerly were needfull, or by taking away ſome <hi>Petitions</hi> which were formerly needfull (it may be at the laſt meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) which are not needfull now: And look upon what grounds it may be lawfull to tye others, or to be tyed by them, to a ſet forme to day, upon the ſame grounds it will be as lawfull to tye them, and to be tyed by them to morrow, the next <hi>Saboth</hi> as well as this, and the third <hi>Saboth</hi> as well as both, and all <hi>Saboths</hi> as well as ſome.</p>
               <p>If tying to ſet forms be lawfull, and thought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, for uniformity in Gods worſhip one day; the ſame uniformity is as expedient to be attended to in every <hi>Saboth,</hi> as in one: or if tying to ſet forms be requiſite to ſupply the defects of the gifts of ignorant Miniſters, then thereby a cloak is made for the covering and ſheltering of ignorant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153145:5"/>Miniſters: who had more need to be ſhouldred ſpeedily out of the Church, than to be ſheltered therein one day to an end. And beſides, if ſuch ſet forms be preſcribed for the ſuccour of ignorant Miniſters, then ſuch Miniſters as have received the gift of prayer, have no need at any time, nor uſe of preſcribed and ſet forms of prayer at all.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>And if it be ſaid that it is not intended, to make it lawfull at any time, to tye or to be tyed to a ſet form of Prayer, ſo as to offer up no more, nor fewer Petitions than what are preſcribed in the Book, but only to warrant the lawfullneſſe of ſome ſet forms of Prayer for ſome occaſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may be juſtly demanded, whether the ſame authority which tyeth to a ſet form of prayer, for ſuch or ſuch occaſions, may not as well tye to a ſet form of prayer for all other occaſions, and if authority may tye the Church to any ſet form of prayer upon any occaſion, whether may not the ſame Authority by the ſame Rule, forbid all other forms of prayers beſides upon the ſame occaſion.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>In Brief (ſay you) the controverſie is, whether it be not lawfull to read a Prayer upon a book, or to make our deſires known in a ſet form of words, when the things we beg, are allowable, fit, and neceſſary, and when it is done with underſtanding, feeling of our wants, faith in Gods promiſes, and reverence of his Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which <hi>Queſtion</hi> you ſpread forth into three branches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether it be lawfull in private to uſe a ſet form of prayer, or upon any occaſion to read as prayer, a prayer upon a Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether a ſet form of prayer ſound, and pertinent, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153145:6"/>the ſubſtance of the matter, grave and ſimple for the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and manner, not prejudiſing, abridging, or hindering by the length thereof, the preaching of the Word; may in any ſort be tollerated in the Church, or read by the Miniſter in the publique Congregation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In caſe it ſhould be unlawfull for the Miniſter or the Maſter of the Family to read a preſcript form of prayer, yet whether it ſhould be unlawfull to be preſent at ſuch aſſemblies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Aſſertion is, that a ſtinted form of prayer is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be uſed both in publique and private, &amp;c. And though it ſhould be ſin in the Miniſter or in the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the family, yet may the people in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the inferiour in the family be preſent at ſuch prayers without ſin or ſcruple of conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How far we go along with you in the <hi>Queſtion</hi> thus ſtated and where we ſtick, may be expreſſed in theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We grant, a Chriſtian man whether Miniſter, or of private place, may by the gift of prayer which he hath received, compile to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ſet form of prayer, and may uſe the ſame for his prayer, whether in publique or private accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his place: yet ſo, as not to limit himſelf to thoſe words: ſeeing he knoweth not what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion may be given him of inlarging his Petitions, by new occurrences of matters from Gods providence, and by the inlargement of the help of Gods Spirit: nor ſo to limit himſelfe as to ſtick long in any ſet form of prayer leaſt it turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a cuſtomary, and empty form, contrary to the watchfullneſſe unto Prayer, which muſt be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly kept of all growing Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A man may give unto another holy dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153145:6"/>and rules for Prayer, and may alſo ſet down ſome forms of prayer as examples of ſuch rules, but not to preſcribe them as ſet forms to them, to be uſed by them for their Prayers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A man that readeth a form of Prayer in a Book, may be ſo affected with it, as in the deſires of his heart to go along with it, and to uſe it for his preſent prayer, as it may thus fall out in reading one of <hi>Calvins</hi> prayers, printed after his Lectures, or ſuch other like.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We deny not, but a man that is affected with ſome Petitions in a Prayer deviſed by others, he may lawfully make uſe of them, and interſert them ordinarily into his own Prayers; But not to take up an intire form of Prayer deviſed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to make it his own ordinary form of Prayer.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We grant Magiſtrates or other Chriſtians may commend ſome Heads or Petitions to the Church according to the preſent ſtate of things (which the Church as they ſee fit) may preſent and commend to God in their Prayers.</p>
               <p>Thus far we conſent, but farther we cannot go, but do rather conceive it to be unlawfull.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſet a part, and take up a ſet form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to uſe it as an ordinary prayer, that which is deviſed by others, whom God hath not called to be a mouth to me.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We conceive it alſo to be unlawfull to bring in ordinarily any other Books, into the publique worſhip of God, in the Church, beſides the Book of God, and therefore do ſee no more warrant to read out of a Prayer Book, the publique Prayers of a Church: then out of a book of <hi>Homilyes</hi> to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153145:7"/>read the publique Sermons of the Miniſters of the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We account it alike (if not more unlawfull) for <hi>Anceſtors</hi> to preſcribe or injoyn ſet forms of Prayers to their poſterity, or for one Church to preſcribe ſet forms of Prayer unto another.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We hold it in like manner unlawfull, for one Church to receive ſuch ſet forms of Prayer from another, and to uſe them for their own Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We take it to be unlawfull alſo, for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God to joyn in ſuch prayers, which are ſo diviſed and preſcribed to be read unto them, and to be offered up in their names, as their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <p>To apply theſe things more punctually to the particular branches of the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſtated by you.</p>
               <p>For your firſt branch, we do not make it a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, whether it be lawfull to make known our deſires in a ſet form of words, in ſuch ſence as we granted above in our firſt point of conſent: nor do we hold it unlawfull to read a prayer upon a book and therein to expreſſe our deſires in ſuch ſort as we granted in our third point of conſent.</p>
               <p>But nevertheleſſe, we do not diſcern it to be lawfull no not in private to uſe ordinarily a ſet form of prayer deviſed by others, nor to read ſuch a prayer out of a book, for the ordinary pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a mans ſelf much leſſe of his <hi>Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For your ſecond Branch, though we neither deny the uſe of ſet form in private, nor in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, ſo it be compiled by a mans own giſts, or by thoſe whom God calleth to be his mouth.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153145:7"/>
               <p>Yet we dare not allow the reading of a ſet form of publique prayer out of a Book penned for the purpoſe, and thoſe prayers compiled by the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Congregation and impoſed upon others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For your third Branch, we for our parts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtifie it to be lawfull for to be preſent, either in the family or in the congregation where, and when ſuch preſcript forms are read for the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the company, as to joyn with them, or to ſeem to joyn with them in ſuch worſhip.</p>
               <p>But proceed we now to conſider the weight of the Reaſons which you give for your judgement and practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Wherein your firſt Reaſon is propounded and conſidered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat Form of prayer</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is juſt and lawfull wherein all things eſſentiall to prayer, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily required in the Word of God may be obſerved:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But all things eſſentiall to prayer, and neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Word of God may be obſerved in read pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or in a preſcript forme; what is required in holy prayer, more then that the matter be allowable and fit, the manner holy, reverend, faithfull, your hearts laid open, and petitions forced with as ſtrong, or ſtronger Reaſons than we are able of our ſelves to preſſe them with all; and may not a prayer holy and fit for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153145:8"/>thereof be read with knowledge, feeling of our wants, earneſtneſſe of our deſires, holineſſe of our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and faith in Gods promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is more required to a faithfull holy prayer, then allowable and fit matter, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inward manner, in the good affections of the heart, for an outward holy manner is required likewiſe, elſe a man might pray to God allowable and fit petitions before an Image; and I deny not, but that God may ſometimes aſſiſt a man in ſuch a prayer with holy manner of inward gracious affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: as for inſtance, holy <hi>Bilney</hi> might find his heart warmed in prayer to Chriſt, when he look'd at him as really preſent in the Sacrament, or elſe he would never have called ſo zealouſly on the people to turn all that adoration of dead Images to the adoration of Chriſt in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nevertheleſſe ſuch a prayer was unlawfull, through a defect in the outward manner of it: an outward means being called in for help in prayer, which God had not ſanctified for that end.</p>
               <p>Let me give you another inſtance, when the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> prayed in the Church publiquely, in the Spirit, but withall in a ſtrange tongue, their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wanted not allowable and fit matter, nor holy inward manner (for they prayed in the ſpirit) yet the prayer was unlawfull through defect of an outward holy manner, becauſe it being put up in a ſtrange tongue before others, did not tend to the edification of others: In the caſe in hand, though prayer upon a Book preſcribed by the authority of man may ſometimes be furniſhed with allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and fit matter, and ſometimes uttered with inward holy affections; yet ſtill it will be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153145:8"/>through the defect of an outward holy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. If ſuch a preſcribed book be found (as we conceive it will) an Image or help to prayer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by men, but not ordained by God, and ſo no better than an Image forbidden in the ſecond Commandement.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>In reading the Scriptures, the eye doth lead the heart, and yet it may be read with judgement, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, meekneſſe, joy, and why may not the like affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be moved in read prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Reading of Scriptures is an Ordinance of God, and not an Image or imagination of man; and therefore God not only may aſſiſt and bleſſe the reading of the Scriptures, with inward good affections, but is uſually wonted ſo to do in an honeſt and good heart, as delighting to breath in his own Ordinances: If it could be proved, that the reading of a preſcript form of prayer upon a Book were an Ordinance of God ſanctified for the edification of the Church (as the reading of the Scriptures is) we might ordinarily expect the like aſſiſtance and bleſſing in reading of the one as well as of the other; the compariſon would be more ſuitable, if inſtead of reading the Scriptures, were put the reading of Sermons and Homilies in the Church, for which we find as little warrant as for reading of Prayers; nor can we expect a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſſing upon the one then upon the other; we do not deny that read prayer may lead and affect the heart, as may a Sermon read at home: But then neither is ſuch a read prayer preſcribed by others, nor ſet a part by me as my prayer; no more than the reading of ſuch a Sermon is my preaching: which is not becauſe the heart and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153145:9"/>the eye are at variance in ſuch a caſe (as your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſpeaketh) but becauſe God doth not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily delight to bleſſe the heart with gracious affections, when the eyes go a whoring after the imaginations and inventions of men.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Aſaph and his Brethren could praiſe God in a form of words, ſet down by the Prophet David; and if a ſet form of words may be allowed in thankſgiving (which is one part of prayer) it cannot be condemned in petitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not deny a ſet-form either of Petition or of thankſ-giving appointed by God, either to be read or ſung, but we deny that God hath allowed either the ordinary officers in his Church (whether <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Levites</hi> in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> in the new) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſuch forms of read prayers for the Church, or the Church to take up ſuch forms of read pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from them; God that hath forbidden us to make any graven Image to our ſelves, hath not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or limited himſelf to deviſe and preſcribe what forms of worſhip himſelf ſhall ſee good for our uſe; the pains which are taken to paralell petitions and thankſgiving might have been ſpared; we neither refuſe the forms of the one, nor of the other, ſuch as are commended to us of God in his Word; the eye doth not hinder the affection of the heart in reading ſuch things as God hath appointed to be read; he that giveth the Word to be read, can give the affections to read it withall, and hath promiſed ſo to do, which the ſons of men that give us preſcript forms of prayer to be read can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153145:9"/>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Whatſoever hath the true matter and form of prayer, is truly and properly prayer; but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of prayer, ſound, and fit for matter; grave for manner of penning, read as prayer with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, reverence and fervency of affection, hath the true matter and form of prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Argument doth not conclude the <hi>Queſtion</hi> in hand; we might grant the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion without prejudice to the cauſe, for a preſcript form of prayer may have the true matter, and eſſential form of prayer, and ſo be (for ſubſtance) truly and properly a prayer, and yet not every way an acceptable and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worſhip of God, through defect of ſome circumſtances which may pertain to externall forme; Baptiſme may be properly and truly baptiſme, as wanting neither true matter nor form, when it is diſpenced by a Miniſter of the Goſpel to a believer or his ſeed by the dipping or ſprinkling of water upon him, <hi>In the name of the Father, the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and yet not every way a lawfull worſhip of God, if it be adminiſtred in an outward form corrupted with the deviſes of men: as with Salt, Cream, Spittle, Croſſe, and the like; ſo is the caſe here; apreſcript form of prayer may conſiſt of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fit petitions, and be delivered with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full holy humble ſpirit, and ſo be truly and properly prayer, and yet fall ſhort of ſome rule requiſite to be attended to make it a lawfull worſhip of God, to wit, if it be offered to God in a ſtrange Tongue or before an Image, or by the help of an Image; ſuch as we conceive a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153145:10"/>preſcript form of words to be injoyned and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, to be read upon a book for the Prayers of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. If by Matter and Form be meant not only Internall and Eſſential forme; but exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall alſo. Then we deny that a preſcript form of prayer injoyned to be read upon a Book, is a lawfull externall form of prayer; no more than a preſcript form of Homilies is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full externall form of preaching; Theſe Anſwers ſeem to us ſufficient and unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and we reſt in them; but the other Anſwers which are alledged by you in your Diſcourſe, and much and often beaten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, though it was delivered by one, whoſe works praiſe him in the gates, throughout all the Churches of the Saints: yet we do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon it, as not willing to turn aſide to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary diſputes, ſtinted ſet forms we do not look at, as lawfull to them that need them; but unlawfull to them that need them not: For though there be a good uſe of the diſtinction in this caſe (as we ſhall ſee anon) yet not in this caſe, where the neceſſity ariſeth not from Gods Commandement, but from the ſinfull defect of the Creature, for ſupply whereof God hath ordained ſufficient help other wayes.</p>
               <p>But yet in reply which you make to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, you give a diſtinction liable to the ſame exception which your ſelf take againſt that Anſwer: For that Anſwer conſiſting of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of arbitrary and neceſſary help.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153145:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Diſcourſe rejecteth it as a diſtinction not grounded upon the Word of God, which in Divinity is</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>an unwritten tradition; and is this diſtinction of your own any better?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helps ſay you and ſurtherances in Gods Service, are of two ſorts, ſome in nature and uſe, the ſame with the true worſhip of God, inſtituted by his highneſſe, and theſe are unlawfull, becauſe they are deviſed; and others concern the Method, Phraſe of Speech, outward manner of celebration, onely as meer circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and theſe are not forbidden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A diſtinction ungrounded upon the Word, &amp; ſo no better that an unwritten tradition, and withall, both the parts imply a falſ-hood; for a prayer which a Miniſter deviſeth for his own, and his peoples uſe, before the Sermon, is in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and uſe the ſame with the true worſhip of God inſtituted by his highneſſe; yet it is not unlawfull becauſe it is deviſed, for it is deviſed by him, who is called of God to deviſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite it, as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. <hi>v.</hi> 1. and all the reſt, and that by help of the Spirit of prayer: again, on the other part, a preſcribed Homilie doth conſerve the method, phraſe of ſpeech, outward manner of celebration, only as a meer circumſtance; yet no Word of God ever al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it to be read for the publick preaching of the Word unto the people.</p>
               <p>It is true which the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>Method</hi> of Sermons, deviſed or ſtudied by ſuch as Preach them, there may be ſome liberty, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to preach by doctrine, reaſon and uſe, or ſome other way; the like may be ſaid of forms
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153145:11"/>of <hi>Chatechiſmes, Bleſſings,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſmes:</hi> But the reaſon of this liberty is becauſe we find in <hi>Scripture</hi> ſeverall forms of all theſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we limit or preſcribe no ſet forms to any; <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> is carried along by Doctrine, reaſons and uſes, and ſo are ſundry more of his Epiſtles. But Chriſts Sermon on the <hi>Mount,</hi> is carried in another <hi>Method: The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Catechiſe is of one form,</hi> Heb. 6.1, 2. <hi>Davids of another,</hi> Pſal. 34.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>The Prieſts Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, were of one form,</hi> Numb. 6.23. to 26. <hi>The Apoſtles Bleſſings of another.</hi> 2 Cor. 12.13.2 Theſ. 3.17, 18. Heb. 13.20, 21. Jude 24.25. <hi>The forms of baptizing did alſo ſometimes vary, ſome uſing the words of our Saviour,</hi> Math. 28.19. <hi>Others ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther form of words,</hi> Acts 19.5. The thing is this, where God hath uſed variety of forms, he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us at liberty to uſe that one form or the other; But to gather a liberty to preſcribe and limit a ſet form of any of theſe, where God hath not limited; is to pervert and abuſe the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the keyes of Chriſts Kingdome: to wit, to bind where Chriſt looſeth, but your <hi>Objection</hi> is (as you ſay) anſwered by others, and that more ſafely.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>That mens inventions in the ſervice of God are forbidden in the ſecond Commandement: But Book Prayer is an Invention of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> replyeth by retorting upon a former <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which we ſaid afore, we did not make uſe of in this caſe.</p>
               <p>You reply again the <hi>Objection</hi> it ſelf is of no weight, for by this reaſon all ſet forms of <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153145:11"/>ſtudied <hi>Sermons,</hi> Interpretations of <hi>Scripture,</hi> diviſions of it into <hi>Sections</hi> and <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> reading one part this week, and another the next, conceived prayer it ſelf may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Touching ſet forms of <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> we do willingly approve diligent attendance to the <hi>Catechiſing</hi> of youth, and <hi>Novices</hi> in any form tending to Edification; but to deviſe and preſcribe a ſet form of words, wherein all the <hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Anſwers</hi> ſhall run, and no other; we know no warrant for that from <hi>Scripture,</hi> if God would have his people limited to a ſet form of words in catechizing: he would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf have preſcribed ſome ſet form of his own inſpiration, which might be defective in no principles, nor incommodious in any expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What though there might be ſome colour to put a ſet form of words of catechiſme into the mouths of Children and Novices, the better to help their memory and capacities; will it therefore argue it to be a reaſonable ſervice of God, to put a ſet form of words and prayers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouths of Miniſters to help their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and capacities, in powring out their own and the Churches Petitions unto God.</p>
               <p>Studied <hi>Sermons</hi> are of another nature, it is an Ordinance of God that <hi>Sermons</hi> ſhould be ſtudied, before preached; <hi>Jude</hi> made it his whole ſtudy, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to write his Epiſtle, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. How much more ought we to make it our whole ſtudy to preach: who are not ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153145:12"/>immediately inſpired. <hi>Solomon</hi> gave good heed and ſought out to find, and ſet in order fit words and matter for the edification of the people, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.9, 10. and behold leſſe than <hi>Solomon</hi> are Miniſters here, though in reſpect of the cleer diſcerning the Myſteries of Chriſt, <hi>The leaſt in the Kingdom of God is greater than he. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monthy</hi> is exhorted to give attendance to read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Meditation, Doctrine, to meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to give himſelf wholly to them, that his profiting might appear to all: That he might ſhew himſelf approved unto God, A work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that needeth not to be aſhamed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15. with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. But give me leave to ſpeak without offence: You ſeem to me in this point to take too much liberty, in a ſerious cauſe to play upon equivocation: It is true, in ſtudying a Sermon the Preacher uſeth his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention and Judgement; and in that ſence his Sermon may be called mans Invention: But you are not ignorant, we ſpeak in this cauſe of ſuch inventions of men, as God hath given neither Commandement nor direction for in his Word; In which ſence a ſtudied Sermon is no more a mans Invention, than a ſtudied an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which <hi>Solomon</hi> commendeth as a path of the Righteous, <hi>Prov:</hi> 15.28. The like may be ſaid of the next inſtance, which is, <hi>Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Scriptures,</hi> as alſo, <hi>a conceived Prayer:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of <hi>Scripture</hi> is from a ſpiritual gift, which God hath given, and commanded to be uſed for the edification of his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.8. So is Prayer conceived from a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153145:12"/>ſpirit and gift of prayer, which is to be uſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and attended to, as a principall part of the Miniſteriall office, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>If it be ſaid, but I may take an Interpretation, or Tranſlation of Scripture from others, and therefore a form of Prayers from others alſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There is a broad difference betwixt an Interpretation of <hi>Scripture,</hi> as it is put for tranſlation of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and read Prayer, for reading of <hi>Scripture</hi> in the Church is an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; ſo is the reading of it in a tongue which the people underſtandeth, and therefore it is an ordinance of God that the Word be read in ſome tranſlation.</p>
               <p>But the reading of a prayer, for the prayers of the Church is no ordinance of God, therefore there is not the like ground from the Word to make uſe of <hi>Prayer-Books,</hi> to read prayers, as to make uſe of a printed Bible for the reading of the Word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every Miniſter that hath underſtanding of the originall languages wherein the <hi>Scripture</hi> was written, ought to make uſe of his own gift in examining the truth of the tranſlation which he readeth unto the Church, which will not be allowed in preſcript <hi>Lyturgies:</hi> As for the diviſion of Scriptures into <hi>Sections</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> and the reading of one part this <hi>Week,</hi> and the other next; It is certain, diviſion of <hi>Scripture</hi> is antient, even from the times of the <hi>Prophets:</hi> And evident it is, the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be read over in one day: And therefore it is from God, that ſome diviſions of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153145:13"/>Scriptures be obſerved, according to the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of matter therein contained, and diſtinctly devideth it ſelfe, and conſequently it is from God, that one part of it be read at this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly another at the next, becauſe all cannot be read at once.</p>
               <p>And yet we know no warrant that one Church ſhould preſcribe another, what diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make of the Scriptures, or what part of it ſhould be read this day, and what the next, what God hath leſt free let no man limit.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Preaching is commanded of God; ſo is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture, but phraſe and method of Interpretation is of men: The matter of the Scripture is the immediate Word of God, but the Word and phraſe, which are Veſſels to convey this truth to us (I ſpeak of Tranſlations not of the Originall Text) are humane and not of God, by immediate inſpiration, God commandeth us to call upon him, both in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and private, but the words in which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our deſires, are our own, both in conceived and ſtinted Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true preaching of the Word and the Interpretation of the Word are of God, but the phraſe and Method is of men, yet ſo of men as they have commandement and warrant from God, to preach and interpret the Word: and not in what phraſe and Method pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: nor in ſuch words as mans wiſdome teacheth, but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. Nor ſo from men as that the men of one Church may deviſe a ſet form thereof, and binde all men, as well of other Churches as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153145:13"/>their own, to this or that manner of phraſe, or Method, the like is to be ſaid of prayer alſo.</p>
               <p>But when your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ſaith, that the words wherein we expreſſe our deſires are our own in conceived and ſtinted prayer, you might as well have ſaid, that the words wherein we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver our Sermons are our own; both in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Sermons, and in ſtinted <hi>Homilies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Theſe two kinds of Prayer (conceived and ſtinted) agree in their Author, Matter, Form, Object, end, and common nature; the one is no more an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of man than the other: ſo then deviſed Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is unlawfull but not a worſhip in a form of words deviſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And ſo might we ſay of prayer to God before an Image, and prayer without an Image; they are two kinds of prayer that agree in their Author, matter, form, object, end, and common nature, yet we cannot ſay the one is more an invention of men than the other: As deviſed Worſhip is unlawfull, ſo are deviſed forms, and means of worſhip unlawfull alſo: of which ſort ſuch ſet forms of words be as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and compoſed by the officers of one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and impoſed upon the brethren of another Congregation, for the forms of their prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. We cannot ſay (as you do) that ſuch conceived and ſtinted forms agree in their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, for I am not the Author of the matter of that prayer which another man compoſed, and was the Author of, and is now ſtinted and preſcribed to me; no more then I can be ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153145:14"/>to be the Author of that Sermon which another man indited. <hi>Battyllus</hi> was not the Authour of <hi>Virgil's</hi> Verſes.</p>
               <p>Though he reſiteth them as his own, <hi>Virgil</hi> juſtly challengeth his own out of his hand, <hi>Hos ego verſiculas feci, &amp;c.</hi> Nor can we ſay that ſuch conceived or ſtinted forms agree in their form, if by form be meant externall form, it is not the ſame form of walking to walk with Crutches, and to walk upright: It is not the ſame form of prayer, to pray with help of mens inventions, and with ſuch helps only as the Holy Ghoſt ſupplyeth: which alſo hindereth that they cannot be ſaid to agree in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature; The one being a lawfull form of prayer, the other unlawfull; And therefore when your Diſcourſe ſaith, that conceived and ſtinted prayer, the one is no more the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man than the other, we cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the truth of that: for in conceived pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Spirit of God within us teacheth us what to pray. And for that the Ordinance and Word of God is plain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. But in ſtinted pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the matter is not ſuggeſted or indited to us by the Spirit of God within us, but preſcribed and impoſed upon us, by the will, wiſdome and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of men; whom the Holy Ghoſt hath not called to ſuch a work: as therefore a devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed worſhip is unlawfull; ſo it is unlawfull to worſhip God in a form of words deviſed by the Officers of one Congregation, and preſcribed and impoſed upon others.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153145:14"/>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Nay</hi> (ſaith your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi>) <hi>for the form of words is not worſhip, but the Prayer tendered in that form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As Prayer is Worſhip, ſo the form in which prayer is offered to God, is <hi>Modus,</hi> or <hi>Medium Cultus,</hi> the manner, or means, or help of Worſhip: which if it be not warranted, and inſtituted of God, it is forbidden in the ſecond <hi>Commandement:</hi> when God forbad his people to worſhip him in ſuch a manner, as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſerved their gods, he ordained them a rule to be perpetually obſerved in all ſervice to him, to wit, that we ſhould worſhip him as himſelf hath commanded, which the oppoſition infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that his meaning is not only with ſuch duties, but in ſuch a manner as himſelf hath commanded, without adding ought thereto or taking ought therefrom, <hi>Deut:</hi> 12.30, 31, 32. <hi>Now he hath commanded us to pray in the ſpirit,</hi> Eph. 6.18. which implies not only with ſuch affections as his Spirit kindleth and ſtirreth up, but alſo with ſuch matter and words as his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit helpeth us unto: For his Spirit is ſaid to help us what to pray, which elſe we ſhould not know, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. Now in a ſtinted preſcript form of prayer, we know what to pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Spirit; when we joyn in prayer with another who is our mouth to God, though we know what to pray by his help, yet it is ſuch an help as the Spirit himſelf hath provided, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>It followeth in the</hi> Diſcourſe, <hi>that mens inventions in Gods worſhip that be of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153145:15"/>and uſe with true worſhip, or with means of worſhip ordained by God, be unlawfull; but method, phraſe, order, of ſpeech deviſed by man, was never judged an invention of man unlawfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This hath been alledged, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered before, but this further let me adde: 1. That the words imply, that mens inventions that be not of the ſame nature and uſe with the worſhip of God, or with the means thereof are lawfull: whereas it is evident that the making of perfume like unto the incenſe of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, though not to the ſame uſe in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but to ſmell at, was rejected of God as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unlawfull, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.38. The making of like things to the ordinances of God, or to the means of worſhip, though not to the like end, but to any religious end, will not be allowed in the ſecond Commandement, as <hi>Gideons</hi> Ephod declareth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe ſet forms of prayer preſcribed to the Churches, we ſee not but that they are of the ſame nature, and enjoyned for the ſame uſe, for which any forms of prayer in Scripture are ordained of God; and therefore by the verdict of your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> they are unlawfull: For as thoſe forms of prayer in Scripture are given of God to ſupply the Church with fit matter for their petitions, and praiſes upon ſundry occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>And for the uſe to the edification of the Church: ſo the forms now in queſtion are of the like nature, given to the like end, only injoyned with more ſtrictneſſe and ſeverity,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153145:15"/>which maketh both their uſe leſſe profitable, and their burthen more heavy, then Gods own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Method, phraſe and order of ſpeech de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by men, was judged an unlawfull inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Paul,</hi> when ſuch wiſdom of words in preaching become not the ſimplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. therefore it cannot be ſaid, that method, phraſe and order of ſpeech deviſed by man, was never judged an unlawfull inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſurely method, phraſe, order of ſpeech deviſed, and preſcribed by one Congregation to another in prayer, doth as little beſeem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and purity of the Goſpel, as the other in preaching did ill become the ſimplicity of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Set prayer is no ſtrange manner of worſhip, becauſe in it all things required to the nature of true prayer may be obſerved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This hath been anſwered before; more goeth to the lawfulneſſe of a prayer then the nature of true prayer; defect in any cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, though but in externall form, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a prayer unlawfull.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>In what method and frame of ſpeech to pray, we find nothing preſcribed of God in particular; neither do we judge any thing neceſſary, more then that order, decency, and edification be regarded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Be it ſo, but how then ſhall men have power to preſcribe to the Churches method and form of ſpeech in prayer, when God hath preſcribed nothing. The Apoſtles, who had the largeſt and higheſt Commiſſion of any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153145:16"/>Church governours in the New Teſtament, yet they had no power to teach, or to preſcribe to the Churches any other things then what Chriſt had commanded them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. Say not, though no other things, yet Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours may command ſuch and ſuch manner of thoſe things: for then a further Commiſſion muſt be ſhown, where Chriſt gave to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or their ſucceſſors power to ordain and preſcribe ſuch and ſuch manner of the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his holy things, as themſelves ſhould ſee good.</p>
               <p>But we never ſaw any ſuch commiſſion held forth to this day from any colour of Scripture light; that only place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. which is alledged in this caſe, is farre off from reaching forth any ſuch authority; for though the place do ſhew that it is the duty of the Church to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter all the holy things of God, in order and decency, and to edification, and to ſee that all things be ſo carried; yet it doth not give to the Church any ſuch power as to make orders, or to ordain forms of decency, or to deviſe means of edification, which himſelf hath not ordained; the Church may indeed appoint ſuch orders, the neglect whereof would be diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and confuſion, as they may appoint one Prophet to ſpeak at once; and when another is called to begin, the firſt to hold his peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the neglect hereof would breed confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Church may appoint ſuch decencies, the neglect whereof would be undecent; as for men to pray bare-headed, and women co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153145:16"/>becauſe the contrary were uncomely by the light of nature, and civill cuſtome; The Church may appoint, and ought to uſe ſuch helps and means to edification, as the Lord hath inſtituted to that end; but if the Church go beyond the bounds of this power they do at once both exceed the bounds of Apoſtolicall authority, and cut ſhort the bounds of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>A ſet form of prayer is for ſubſtance and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture agreeable to the rules of direction delivered in the word of truth, though for method and word it be humane, as conceived prayer is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſet form of prayer, as it is ſet by one Congregation for another, can find no rule of direction, nor any foot-ſtep thereof in the word of truth.</p>
               <p>In ſaying that for method and words, a ſet form of prayer is humane, as conceived prayer is; there is the like liberty taken of Sophiſtry, in an equivocation, which was obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for though a conceived Prayer may be ſaid to be humane, as it is conceived and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the heart of a man, and by man offered as worſhip to God (as all other holy duties be in this ſenſe humane) yet ſuch a conceived prayer being indited by the Spirit of God in the heart of him that prayeth, and being expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Word: it cannot be truly called an humane invention, which is only ſpoken of thoſe things as have neither commandement, nor pattern from the Word, in which ſenſe we called a ſet form humane.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153145:17"/>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>If our Brethren diſpair not of the goodneſſe of their Cauſe; let them in an orderly Treatiſe ſet down what is neceſſary and eſſentially required, to the nature and being of true Prayer, and then ſhew that ſome one or other of them cannot be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a ſtinted or Preſcript forme of Prayer, and we will readily yeeld unto them; and ſome Reaſon or pregnant place of Scripture, ſhall put us to ſilence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſee no cauſe to diſpair of the goodneſſe of the cauſe, which we conceive is not ours but Gods; we chooſe rather to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the ſinfulneſſe of our former courſe, then eagerly to diſpute for our preſent proceedings; we all of us have ſinned with our Brethren, and with our Fathers in worſhipping God after the precepts of men, and have as much cauſe to judge our ſelves for it, as you have: To write a Treatiſe of all the requiſites to true prayer, is nothing to the ſtanding or falling of the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>As hath been ſaid, prayer may be true, and have all thoſe things which are neceſſary and eſſentially requiſite to true prayer, and yet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully def ective in ſome extenall circumſtances: It were much more pertinen to write a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Second Commandement, whereunto the conſideration of the helps and Forms of Worſhip doth properly belong; &amp; from thence to conſider whether any ſound reaſon at laſt (which you deſire) may not be inferred againſt preſcript Forms of Prayer.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore conſider together of the meaning of that <hi>Commandement,</hi> though not in the full latitude of it (for that were not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153145:17"/>to the Cauſe in hand) but ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the preſent buſineſſe; and yet not ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, nor ſtriving to put you to ſilence, but to awaken both our ſelves and you (if it be the Will of God) to repentance.</p>
               <p>The Second <hi>Commandement,</hi> in forbidding Images, forbiddeth not only bodily Images, (Graven or Molten, or Painted) but all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Images alſo; which are the Imaginations and Inventions of men, whether they be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for worſhip (as <hi>Apocrapha</hi> Scriptures, and the Lawes of men binding the Conſcience) or for helps and means of worſhip (as ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremonies, to teach and ſtir up to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Duties) or finally, for formes, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhip, yet when we ſpeak of helps and means of worſhip invented by Men, and forbidden by God, in this Commandement we doe not ſpeak either of naturall or artificiall helps to help the natural ſenſe in Gods worſhip; (ſuch as Scaffolds be to mens hearing) nor of the helps of Tongues and Arts which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God hath given for an help to the mind and underſtanding in all knowledge: As if God commanded the people to read in his Word all their dayes, and to read with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Tranſlation of Scripture into the Mother-Tongue of each Nation, is a neceſſary help to this end, &amp; the knowledg of grammer, &amp; tongues is a neceſſary help to ſuch a tranſlation.</p>
               <p>And ſo if God command the people to joyne together, as well in voyce as in heart, to ſing <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and to ſing them with underſtanding; ſeeing <hi>Pſalmes</hi> are a kind of holy Poetry, even
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153145:18"/>as Grammar will be a neceſſary help to tranſlate the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> So Poetry will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to tranſlate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into verſe; and ſuch kind of helps, though they be not expreſly commanded by God, yet we look at them as warranted by neceſſary conſequence from the Word; becauſe God, who commanded thr du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Reading the Scripture, and ſinging of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> (and both to be done with underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) he doth imply a neceſſary warrant of ſuch means as do naturally and neceſſarily lead to thoſe ends, and without which thoſe ends (without a miracle cannot be otained.</p>
               <p>We ſpeak therefore of ſuch means and helps of worſhip forbidden in this Commandement, not which do naturally and neceſſarily help forward the ſame (though remotely) but of ſuch Arbitrary helps, as are voluntarily taken up by the wiſdome and will of man for ſpirituall ends, (as <hi>Gideons</hi> Ephod and <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſuperadded to thoſe means and helps of worſhip; which God hath ſufficiently, yea, and abundantly ſupplyed, his Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple withall, by his Word and Spirit, for all ſpirituall duties.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, this diſtinction of voluntary and neceſſary helps, may not be ſtretched ſo farre, as to juſtifie deviſe and ſet forms of Prayer, to ſupply the defects of ſinfully igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or careleſly baſhfull people, as cannot pray (eſpecially before company) without a book: For, firſt, God would not have ſuch perſons (ſo ſinfully ignorant and baſhfull) to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153145:18"/>called forth into publique Miniſtry; the lame and the blind ſhall not come into <hi>Sion,</hi> into <hi>Davids</hi> Houſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.8. nor may ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and lame Chriſtians be admitted to come into the publick place in the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God hath provided other ſufficient helps to ſupply theſe defects to private Chriſtians: for beſides the Spirit of God (which helps all our infirmities <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.) who ſupplieth both the ignorant with knowledge of what, and how to pray, and the baſhfull with power; he hath alſo ordained inſtruction to help the ignorant, and frequent exerciſe, and diligent Catechiſing of a mans own family, to help his baſhfulneſſe in praying before them; and if ſtrangers come in, (and they ſit to partake in ſuch an ordinance) God then offereth him the help of a Chriſtian friend to ſupply his neceſſity before ſtrangers; and when we ſpeak of form, and manner of worſhip deviſed by men; we ſpeak not of ſuch as light of nature and civill cuſtome taketh up for order and decency: but of ſuch as are taken up by the voluntary choice of the wiſdome and will of man, either for ſuch ends as God hath not appointed (as uniformity in Rites, and conformity to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) or for ſuch ends, as for which God hath provided otherwiſe; as the Love-feaſts in the Church to maintain brotherly love, for which God ordained the Lords Supper, and feaſts in private houſes: or contrary to ſuch ends and wayes as God hath appointed, as the <hi>Chemarines</hi> to offer incenſe, (a type of Prayer) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153145:19"/>a Praying Miniſtry, without ſacrificing; as a read Liturgie to maintain a reading or praying Miniſtry without preaching.</p>
               <p>It was touched upon before that, when God forbad us ſuch a manner of worſhip, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens uſe to their god, and againſt that one falſe manner of worſhip, eſtabliſheth his own inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions in his Word (<hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30, 31, 32.) He doth thereby evidently condemn under one falſe manner of worſhip all other forms or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of worſhip, which are not inſtituted in his word. Hence conformity to Idolaters in cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their hair and beards is forbidden, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.27. Hence preaching in the wiſdome of words, (or in carnall eloquence) is forbidden: as a painted Image againſt the ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 21. Hence Prayer towards the Eaſt falleth under the ſame reproof: Hence the incenſe of <hi>Uzzia,</hi> the ſtrange fire of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu;</hi> the ſtriking of the rock by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Wilderneſſe of <hi>Sin;</hi> the Love-Feaſts brought into the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>And many more ſuch like forms and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Gods worſhip are forbidden in the Word, as divers from the rule and pattern held forth in the ſecond Commandement, as it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and illuſtrated by theſe and ſuch like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the writings of the Prophets, and Apoſtles: we are not ignorant that there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a ſinfull form and manner of worſhip which is forbidden in the third Commandement, as when we worſhip God unreverently, or drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fily, but that is rather <hi>Ro. modus colendus,</hi> then <hi>modus cultus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153145:19"/>
               <p>To apply then to this Rule and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God theſe ſet forms of Prayer deviſed by men, and preſcribed to be read out of a Book, and ſo taken up by one Church from another, as the forms of their worſhip, and the helps of their devotion: We find no Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement nor Pattern for them in the Word; nor any promiſe for their acceptance; They are injoyned for helps, and means of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; which God hath not ſanctified, and for forms of worſhip, which God hath not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and therefore we know not how to excuſe them from ſin, againſt the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſecond Commandement.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>If it be ſaid that it was granted, before in ſtating the Queſtion, that in reading a Prayer penned by another man</hi> (<hi>ſay one of</hi> Calvins <hi>Prayers after his Lectures</hi>) <hi>a man may be ſo affected with it, as that his heart going along therewith, he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey his own deſires, and Petitions to God in reading thereof, and ſo make it his own Prayer, though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by another, and read out of a Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We grant that a man may make uſe of another mans penned Prayers read in private, not only for an example, or inſtruction how to pray; but alſo occaſionally for his preſent Prayer; If he find the Petitions ſutable to his preſent occaſions: Yea, we grant further, that in caſe one Church ſhould ſend letters to another Church, and in the end thereof ſhould conclude with ſome Prayer ſuitable to the ſtate of the Church to whom they write: we doubt not but that the Church to whom the letters
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153145:20"/>are ſent, finding the Petitions ſuitable to their condition, may lawfully go along therewith in ſpirit, and in the end ſay <hi>Amen</hi> thereto, and ſo make it their own Prayer.</p>
               <p>But yet here be two things different from the caſe in hand.</p>
               <p>Firſt, They that penned ſuch Prayers did not preſcribe them as forms of Prayer for the brethren to uſe, left them freely to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that take them up occaſionally for their preſent uſe, and make them their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they do not ſet them apart to be read for their ordinary Prayers, either in publique or in private, which ſeemeth to us a matter of weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſideration, and maketh a great difference in the cauſe in hand to clear it by a familiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: A man paſſing through a burying place may ſee a dead mans ſcalp caſt up, and thereby take occaſion from the preſent object to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate (for the preſent) on his mortality, and to prepare for like change: but if he ſhall take up, and keep that dead mans ſcalpe in his Cloſet, or Bed chamber, to be an ordinary help to him, to put him in mind daily of his mortality: Now in ſo doing he maketh an Image of it, to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by ſetting it a part to be an help to him in Gods worſhip; which not being ſanctified and ſet a part by God for that end, it now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſin to him againſt the ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in the former caſe, he took occaſion to fall into a preſent good meditation of mortality, by the preſent ſight of an object of mortaliy,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153145:20"/>as it was ſet before him occaſionally by Gods providence, wherein he did well according to the ſecond Commandement, not to paſſe by ſuch a paſſage of Gods providence in vain: But in the latter caſe in ſetting it a part to be an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary help to him in ſuch meditations, or injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame to others; He in ſo doing maketh it to him and them an Image, it not being inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, or ſanctified by God, but deviſed and ſet apart by man, for ſuch a ſpirituall end, which is forbidden in the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid again, when I read Prayer and ſind ſome Petitions therein that ſute well with my eſtate, I may not only then uſe them for my preſent Prayer, but may again and again ordinarily make uſe thereof in my own Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny not that, but it is one thing to take up a Petition, or two, or more, and to inſert them here and there into mine own Prayers, and another thing to take up a whole intire prayer, or form of prayer, and uſe it ordinarily as mine own; ſee the like in Preaching, I may make uſe of a ſentence or two, or more, here and there out of another mans Sermon, and it may be inculcate the ſame again and again, in many Sermons together of my own; But I may not therefore take up a whole Sermon penned by another, and preach it for mine own, though it were never ſo fit for my Text, and for mine own Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153145:21"/>
               <p>Whence alſo another reaſon (and in our apprehenſion of juſt weight) may be alledged againſt the ordinary uſe of ſet forms of Prayers deviſed by others. If every Miniſter be to edifie the Church by the diſpenſation of his own tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, and gifts, as well in prayer as in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Then he may not pray another mans pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned prayer, no more then preach another mans penned Sermon, but the former is true, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.11, 12, 13. therefore the latter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let me adde a third reaſon, If I may worſhip God in the <hi>congregation</hi> with a ſet form of prayer, read out of a book, then I may bring into the Church another book beſides the book of God, to be read ordinarily for the publique edification of the Church: But we know no warrant for the uſe of any book in the Church to be read ordinarily for the publique edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church; beſides the book of God; to bring into the Church any other book beſides Gods, is like the bringing in of another <hi>Altar</hi> into the Temple of the Lord, and ſet it up beſides the <hi>Altar</hi> of the Lord: which did in time thruſt the <hi>Altar</hi> of the Lord to ſtand behind, and give place, and at length to be laid aſide, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.14, 15. I need not apply it, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence goeth far enough in applying of it; If it be an unſanctified way of preaching to fill a Sermon with <hi>Quotations,</hi> out of the Books of ancient Divines (whom more commonly then ſafely they call Fathers) though the ſentences be godly, and pithy, how much more will it be an unſanctified kind of prayer, to make up not only many Petitions together, but alſo a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153145:21"/>whole form of Prayer out of a book, leſſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and much more offenſive.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let me conclude with a fourth reaſon, and adde no more in this place, He that ſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth a few prayers which in themſelves are free from offenſive matter but of a book lyable (in the whole bulke) to many juſt exceptions, and withall impoſed by one Church upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he doth really therein hold forth and profeſſe his ſubjection (not only to the irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar exerciſe of that authority, whereby it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned) but alſo to the whole order of worſhip injoyned in that book; as <hi>Paul</hi> in practiſing (though but ſeldome) a few ceremonies out of the book of the Law, did therein hold forth and profeſſe his orderly walking according to the whole Law, and his proſeſſed ſubjection to the whole order of worſhip preſcribed by the authority of the Law, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.24.25, which had it not been warranted by God himſelf fora ſeaſon, he had doubtleſs thereby ſinned againſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement, Since then the ſecond Commandement is ſo many wayes violated by reading of a Prayer-book, deviſed and preſcribed by humane authority, for the publique Prayers of the Church, the Lord pardon all our provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of his jealouſie by our former ignorance in this point, &amp; keep us blameleſſe for after times, for his holy names ſake, in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know the ſinnes againſt this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, do more provoke the jealouſie of the Lord againſt his people, and that for many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, then the breach of any of the reſt, which is the reaſon why the Lord ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153145:22"/>his people (as a flaming ſword) his jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, for a ſanction and fence of this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above the reſt, <hi>Eaeod.</hi> 20.5. And ſhall we then provoke the Lord to jealouſie, are we ſtronger than he? but let us proceed with our Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>They tell us</hi> (ſay you) <hi>God hath not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a ſet preſcript worſhip, he hath not indeed preſcribed it as neceſſary, but his Word doth warrant it to us as lawfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, ſhew us, but one Text of the word that doth warrant it as lawfull, any word of precept or promiſe, or pattern from the Scripture, and we ſhall do as you offer to do, ſit down in ſilence.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if God hath not preſcribed a ſet form as neceſſary, why is ſuch neceſſity put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Churches, for receiving of it, hath the Church power to bind where God looſeth?</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Touching the externall form of words, in which we ſhould profer our Petitions, we know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing preciſely commanded by the Lord, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge it a thing meerly indifferent whether our requeſts be read or uttered; whether in a ſtinted or conceived form of words; neither do we bring in any ſtrange manner of Prayer; for in ſubſtance the prayer read and conceived is all one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, touching the externall form of words in prayer, we may know (and muſt willingly know what the word hath taught us) that the Lord hath commanded (whether expreſſely or by juſt conſequence, all is one):</p>
               <p>Firſt, that as in Preaching, ſo conſequently
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153145:22"/>in Prayer, we are to expreſſe our minds in ſuch a frame of words, not which mans wiſdome teacheth, but which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> teacheth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that we are not to worſhip God after the precepts, or patterns of men, but do all things after the pattern in the mount, <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30, 31, 32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that we ſhould not worſhip God in an Image, deviſed by man, and ſuch are all ſet forms of Prayer, deviſed helps of worſhip, and preſcribed to be read in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. But ſuppoſe (as the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that it were a thing meerly indifferent, whether our requeſts be read, or uttered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a ſtinted or conceived form of words, It ſeemeth to us a manifeſt tranſgreſſion of the bounds, both of Apoſtolicall authority, and Chriſtian liberty, to bring in or take up a form of Prayer ſtinted and limitted by men, which is left to us indifferent by God; nor can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a read prayer preſcribed by men, from a ſtrange form of prayer; ſeeing no ſuch form is read or heard of, in all the Scripture; ſo great a difference is there betwixt a conceived, and preſcribed read prayer, as is betwixt the fire from the Altar and the ſtrange fire; the one is an ordinance of God, the other is an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153145:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Wherein Anſwer is returned to Reaſon the ſecond.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF it be lawfull to uſe a preſcript form of bleſſing, prayer thanks-giving, and baptiſing ſet down in the Word of God, Then all preſcript forms of Prayer or Liturgy, are not to be condemned; but the former appeareth from</hi> Numb. 6.22, 23. Pſal. 102.1. Hoſ. 14.2, 3. Joel 2.17. Deut. 5.10. Pſal. 92.1. Ezra. 3.10. Rev. 15.3.2 Chron. 29.30. Iſa. 12.1. Math. 28.19. <hi>What anſwer do our Brethren re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to this Argument?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our anſwer is ready, and plain, juſt and ſhort, we deny both the Major Propoſition, and the ground of the Minor; for (to ſpeak firſt to the former) it doth not follow that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of prayer invented by men is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe a form preſcribed of God is good and allowable; the Reaſon whereof is ſound and evident; though God forbid men to make themſelves any Image, or likeneſſe in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet he hath not forbidden himſelfe this power to preſcribe any Image or form to us; he appointed his people to make the Cherubims to worſhip him before them, both in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle and Temple; but yet when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made to himſelf the like form at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153145:23"/>and preſcribed them to the people, it was a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt breach of the ſecond Commandement; what reply doth the Diſcourſer return to this?</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>A meer ſhift</hi> (ſay you) <hi>inſtead of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: for the queſtion is not of this or that form in particular, but of a preſcript form in it ſelfe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; the Lords Prayer was indited, or preſcribed by our Saviour himſelf, and they yet deny the uſe thereof as a prayer, and moſt of the Reaſons which they bring, do conclude againſt every ſet form of prayer, as well as againſt any one; thus they argue: If a ſet form of Prayer be lawfull, then a man may carry his prayers in his pocket; buy them at the Book-binders ſhops, &amp;c. and doth not this Reaſon diſallow all penned and printed formes as well as ours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus, with one ſudden and blunt daſh of a Pen, a holy and divine truth confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by plentifull evidence of Scripture, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed generally and frequently by our beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines againſt Popiſh Images, is at once blotted out, and branded as a ſhift: I ſay no more but this: This is a ſpeaking evill of the Law; and condemning of the Law, and that in a higher degree than that which is reproved by the Apoſtle <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 4.11. for the Law it ſelf in condemning Images, and the imaginations of mens deviſing, commandeth and eſtabliſheth the Images and imaginations ordained by God.</p>
               <p>Therefore for you to call ſuch a diſtinction of Images, as is eſtabliſhed by the Law of God,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153145:24"/>a meer ſhift, is to make your ſelf (pardon my plainneſſe) in this caſe, not an obſerver of the Law, but a Judge; ſo farre will inordinate zeale to a way of error tranſport even godly minds.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeak to the grounds of ſuch a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, though it were granted that the queſtion is not of this or that form of Prayer in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet is of a ſet form deviſed by men, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to be read out of a book for an ordinary Prayer; yea, I might adde further, that the occaſion of the Queſtion in hand, ſpringeth from an offence taken at ſome brethren (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the letters ſent to us about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by ſundry Reverend godly brethren, and ſubſcribed amongſt others, by your own name) for their not joyning with others to worſhip God in a common ſtinted Liturgy, known to be deviſed by men, and preſcribed to be read for the publique Prayers of all the Churches in the Countrey; howſoever therefore the queſtion be reduced by your Diſcourſes <hi>ab Hypotheſi, ad Theſin</hi> (&amp; by lawfull rules of diſpute ſo may be) yet it is againſt the rule <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo to palliate the matter, as to draw the queſtion above the kind, and occaſion of the queſtion, you may upon occaſion of one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of Prayer deviſed by men, put the queſtion of any preſcript form of Prayer devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by men; but it is an utter changing and forſaking of the cauſe to put off the queſtion in hand to forms of Prayer deviſed and preſcribed by God; what though ſome that have ſpoken
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153145:24"/>or written in this cauſe, have waved ſome forms of Prayer deviſed by God himſelf; and have uſed ſome arguments, that graſp at more than they can hold?</p>
               <p>The ſtate of the queſtion muſt not be drawn to the arguments, but the arguments to the ſtate of the queſtion; It is true, ſome have doubted, and ſome have denyed the uſe of the Lords Prayer (as it is called) for a Prayer, but they would never have denyed it or doubted of it, if they had thought it had been preſcribed by Chriſt for a Prayer: But howſoever (not to ſpend words and time in vain) we for our parts (I ſpeak for the moſt part) do grant it may be lawfull to pray thut very Prayer, in the ſame words, and yet this will not at all prejudice the cauſe in hand, to juſtifie Prayers in a Book compoſed by men, and impoſed by one Church upon another.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, that Argument againſt ſuch Prayers which are fetched from the Topicks of the Pocket, or of the Book-binders Shops, we neither uſe, nor allow, they which uſe them may clear their own intentions and drift in them.</p>
               <p>Having thus cleared the denyall of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Propoſition, we do as juſtly deny the ground of the Minor, for though it do appear from Scripture, that ſome forms of Prayer, or bleſſing, or baptizing, or thankſgiving deviſed by God, were ſometimes uſed by godly men (and it was lawfull for them ſo to do) yet we deny (that which was the ground of the Minor)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153145:25"/>that God in his Word did ſet down any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of any of theſe: Preſcript (I ſay) In ſuch a ſence as in this Queſtion is intended; to wit, preciſely injoyning the uſe thereof in all their publique holy Aſſemblies: nor will any of the Scriptures alledged reach that; in <hi>Numb,</hi> 6.22, 23. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> are directed to a form of bleſſing: But that they uſed that and not other forms, doth not appear: It is evident that the Apoſtles uſed divers other forms, as hath been ſhewed above, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1. there is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of a form of words at all, only Chriſt uſed the ſame words, with a little variance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like occaſion, on the Croſſe, or if you urge the title of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> from <hi>Junius</hi> his notes, as if the <hi>Pſalm</hi> were appointed to be ſung every morning by break of day: Bear with us if we rather fetch the meaning of theſe words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the <hi>Pſalm</hi> it ſelf, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. where the Prophet alluding to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> calleth the Lord <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> my ſtrength haſten to help me, the words therefore in the title hold forth no more but the Argument of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for ſpeedy help a <hi>Pſalm</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> In <hi>Pſalm</hi> 102.1. the Title ſheweth what an afflicted ſoul in ſuch a caſe did pray; but doth not preſcribe all afflicted ſoules to powre out the ſame form of words in their afflictions. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.2, 3. The Prophet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth them to take words to themſelves, to ſuch a purpoſe: But whether the ſelf ſame words, or ſome other ſuch like, he doth not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or preſcribe: The like may be ſaid of <hi>Joel.</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153145:25"/>1.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.10. hath nothing ſounding to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the point in hand. I ſuppoſe it is miſwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the errour of the Scribe. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.1. the Pſalm is penned for the Sabbath, but whether for a word of inſtruction for the Sabbath, or for thankſgiving on the Sabbath it is not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, we willingly grant it was penned for both; But nevertheleſſe, it was not preſcribed every Sabbath day to be ſung. In <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.10. it doth appear, as alſo 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.30. That they praiſed God with the words of <hi>David</hi> and after his Ordinance: But his Ordinance and words were appointed by God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25. And yet not ſo preſcribed to be uſed as never to be omitted; In <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. when it is ſaid, they ſung the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of God, and the Song of the Lamb; It is only meant, they praiſed God with Pſalms to the like effect as that of <hi>Moſes;</hi> not with the ſame words, much leſſe upon preſcript. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.1. It is propheſied the Church ſhall praiſe God to ſuch a purpoſe as theſe words hold forth: But whether in theſe very words, is uncertain, certain it is, they are not ſo preſcribed to do; but left at liberty. In <hi>Matth.</hi> 29.19. the place is miſwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as before.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>But it ſufficeth us that theſe forms of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Prayer, might lawfully be uſed as a bleſſing, or Prayer, though in conſcience they were not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily tyed to the uſe of them: The lawfull, not the neceſſary uſe of a preſcript form of prayer (or liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) is now in queſtion: for if the Saints in former times might pray unto God, or praiſe him in a ſtinted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153145:26"/>form of words, indited by others, or invented by themſelves (as we find they might and did) we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo at this day do the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny not that forms of Prayer and bleſſings indited by the Holy Ghoſt in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may be lawfully ſo uſed, but we deny that they were preſcribed, or limited to be ſo uſed, but ſtill the Church left at liberty to uſe them, or ſome other holy forms in their ſtead; and therefore when the Diſcourſe ſaith the lawfull, not the neceſſary uſe of a preſcript form, is now in queſtion, you make the queſtion to imply a contradiction: for a preſcript form is put upon the Churches, as neceſſary to be uſed in all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique holy aſſemblies, elſe it is not a form pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, but deſcribed only.</p>
               <p>Diſc, <hi>But</hi> (ſaith the Diſcourſer) <hi>if they will hear with patience, the conſequence of that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, The uſe of a deviſed, and preſcribed form of prayer will be juſtified from their own ground; for they teach that God hath not appointed in his Word any preſcript form, which of neceſſity we are tyed to uſe at all; that the matter of our prayers are divers, according to the ſeverall occaſions, which happen and fall out; that the Inward frame is the elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoul to God, in humility, love, fear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; from which premiſes it will neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if one godly forme of prayer may be uſed, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo fit for matter, grave for phraſe of ſpeech, may be allowed, for none is abſolutely commanded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The contrary concluſion doth rather follow from the premiſes; for if none be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely commanded by God, then none ought to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153145:26"/>be commanded or preſcribed by men; what God hath left free in his worſhip, let no man limit; To what Church did God ever give power to bind where himſelf looſeth? And if it be unlawfull for Church Governours to bind where God looſeth, it will be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the people ſo deeply to offend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Governours, as to build them up, or to harden them in their ſins, by ready ſubjection to ſuch injunctions, and ſerious and zealous pleading for them: How much ſafer were it for the people of God, to ſtand faſt in the liberty which Chriſt hath purchaſed for them, in accepting no other yoke of ordinances, nor forms of worſhip, then himſelf hath put upon them? that ſo Church Governours might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves within the power in Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, wherein the Lord hath contained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe throughout the Scriptures; when ſhall it once be that the ſervants of God will learn to be wiſe, and teach others to be wiſe, not above that which is written, but according to it, that ſo an end might be put at length to the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and innovations of the ſons of men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they take upon themſelves an uſurpation beyond the bounds of Apoſtolicall Authority, and put upon the people an unjuſt reſtraint of the bounds of their dear bought Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty?</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>The uſe of a preſcript form of prayer (or Liturgy) derogateth</hi> (as ſome ſay) <hi>from the honour, fruit and benefit of Chriſts aſcention; who aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up on high, hath given gifts to men for the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153145:27"/>work of the Miniſtry,</hi> Eph. 4.8. <hi>Let it be granted that every particular Miniſter is able in ſo full and ample manner at all times to open his heart before God (which can never be proved) as that he ſhall not need the help of a book; Is there no warrant therefore for others to preſcribe, or for themſelves to read or uſe ſtinted prayer; why not? an able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hath diſcretion to know what portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is fit to be read; Hath the Church then no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to appoint what Books and Chapters ſhall ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be read; or hath a Miniſter no warrant to obſerve that appointment? A learned Linguiſt is able to tranſlate a Chapter in the old or new Teſtament, peradventure as well as it is tranſlated, may not the Church yet ordain one uſually to be read?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let our brethren judge the ſtrength of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in one framed after the ſame manner; If a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter be indued with gifts to judge what portion of Scripture is meet to be read, then is there no warrant for another to preſcribe, nor for them to read ſtinted portions of Scripture preſcribed by men; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is a part of Gods worſhip, ſo is reading of Scripture; the externall form of words are humane, ſo is the preſcription of ſuch a Book or Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Reaſon is of more weight againſt preſcript forms, then will ſo eaſily be caſt off, at leaſt to our beſt apprehenſions; For if the Lord Jeſus by his aſcention hath given ſufficient furniture of gifts to the Miniſters of his Church for prayer, as well as for preaching; For the whole work of the Miniſtry, for the edification
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153145:27"/>of the Church, For the perfecting of the Saints unto the fulneſſe of the ſlature of the age of Chriſt; Then it is diſhonourable unto Chriſt, and ſuperfluous for the Governours of the Church, to preſcribe unto Miniſters ſet forms of Prayer in Liturgies, any more than ſet forms of preaching in Homilies; If Chriſt hath not gifted them as ſufficient for the one as for the other, it doth indeed derogate from the honour and fruit of his aſcention; if he have, then it is ſuperfluous for Church governours, <hi>Actum Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> even as much as to tie bladders under the wings of Sea-fowls to keep them from ſinking, or to help them to ſwim; It is true that every good Miniſter is not able at all times to open his heart to God in Prayer, but neither is he able at all times to open the mind of God in preaching, but if he be not able to do both without book, neither will he be able to do either upon a book preſcribed to him; I have known a Miniſter to edifie the people more by ſilence in the Pulpit through ſtrength of temptation, then ever I knew any do by reading a Homily upon the Book.</p>
               <p>If an able Miniſter have diſcretion to know what portion of Scripture is fit to be read, to what end ſhould the Church appoint him what Books and Chapter to read ordinarily; It is a commendable work in any ſtate to procure a faithfull tranſlation of the Bible to be extant in the mother tongue of each people under their dominions, for the common benefit of them all. And we do eaſily grant a Miniſter (though he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153145:28"/>be a learned Linguiſt) hath liberty not onely to make uſe of it in his private ſtudies, but alſo to make uſe of it in the Congregation; for ſeeing reading of Scripture is an ordinance of God; yea, and reading of it in the mother tongue of each people, it will beſt agree with the edification of each people, to read it out of ſuch a book as is frequent and currant in all their hands.</p>
               <p>But yet the Church may not ſo bind him to ſuch a tranſlation, as not to give him leave to amend it, if need be; and he be able: And beſides, this will no way reach the binding of Miniſters to a ſet form of Prayer upon a book: ſeeing reading of Prayers in the Church, as Prayers, is not any ordinance of God; as all the reading of tranſlated Scriptures be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153145:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Anſwering to the third Reaſon.</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>IF it be lawfull to ſing Pſalmes in a form of words deviſed by men, then likewiſe to pray unto God in a ſtinted forme; If the one of theſe be an invention of men a ſtrange prayer; a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a prayer: ſo is the other a ſimilitude of a Pſalm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, the ſinging of Pſalms (whereof you ſpeak) in a form of words deviſed by men, may have a double meaning: for either you mean ſuch Pſalms as are compiled by ordinary men, or elſe Pſalms penned by the Prophets; but tranſlated by ordinary men into Engliſh verſe, to be ſung in the Churches; If you ſpeak of the former, then this is our firſt anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. We ſee as little warrant for ſinging <hi>Apocrypha</hi> Pſalms in the Church, as for praying preſcript <hi>Lyturgies</hi> of men in the Church: and for both together, as little warrant as for reading <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha</hi> Scriptures in the Church; but if you ſpeak of the latter, then our ſecond anſwer is this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is an obſervable difference between ſinging of Pſalms and Prayer; as alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Pſalms penned by the Prophets, and by other ordinary men; for in the peoples joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153145:29"/>in prayer, there is no more required but their going along in ſilence, with conſent of the heart, and in the end of the prayer, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their conſent in voyce, by ſaying, <hi>Amen,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14.16. But in ſinging of Pſalms, all the people of God (as ſpiritual Prieſts) do ſing with voyce together, according to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.8. which putteth a neceſſity upon a ſet form of Pſalms, elſe one ſhould ſing one thing, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther another thing, which would inſtead of harmony, breed confuſion; but there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a ſet form of Prayer; for if the words of the Miniſters prayers be underſtood of the people, they go along &amp; joyn with him in ſilent conſent, as well in a form conceived for the preſent occaſion; as in a ſet form of words, whereunto they have been accuſtomed: beſides the Pſalms penned by the Prophets (as by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and the reſt) being of divine inſpiration, and part of the holy word of God (which we are commanded ſhould dwell in us plenteouſly, and wherewith we are to teach and admoniſh our ſelves and one another, by the ſinging of them unto the Lord) we have therefore a lawfull warrant, to ſing ſuch Pſalms; even in ſuch a form of words, as they are tranſlated into by men; when yet we have not the like war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to pray the forms of Prayer deviſed by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary men, which are not of divine inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of humane invention and injunction. Pſalms and Scripture tranſlated are ſtill as truly the Word of God in the tranſlation, as in the originall language.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153145:29"/>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>If a man be diſpoſed to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the ſinging of Pſalms, he may a great deal more plauſibly argue that the infancy of the Church when God ſaw a ſet form to be neceſſary; he inſpired holy men to pen ſuch as might be of uſe for that time, when ſuch worſhip was approved; and therefore ſeeing at this day, no ſuch forms are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us of God, they are not to be allowed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such an argument though you think it were plauſible, yet indeed it is leſſe defence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; for the truth is, ſet forms of Pſalms are as neceſſary now, as they were then; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is neceſſary that all the people ſhould joyn in voyce as well as in heart, in the ſinging of Pſalms. It is therefore neceſſary they ſhould know before-hand the ſame ſet form of words in which they ſhould all joyn; and ſeeing a ſet form of words in Pſalms is neceſſary, it pleaſed the Lord to deviſe himſelf to our hands a ſet form of them by his holy Prophets; who being carried by the Holy Ghoſt, farre above humane infirmity and poſſibility of erring; they have ſet down ſuch forms as were fit not only for the infancy of the Church, but for the publique uſe of all Churches in all ages, and for all occaſions, which cannot be ſaid of any compilements de viſed by ordinary men.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>a ſet form of words is as neceſſary in preaching, and publique prayers, as in ſinging; this or that form is neceſſary in neither; a ſet form is neceſſary in both; the people cannot ſing with the Miniſter, unleſſe what is ſung be repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them in a ſet form of words; nor can they joyn in prayer, or attend to the word preached, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153145:30"/>the matter of praying or preaching be conveyed to them in a ſet form of words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> You confound a form of words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and a ſet form: it is true, no man can joyn in prayer, or attend unto the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, unleſſe the matter of prayer or preaching be conveyed in a form of words underſtood: but yet without a ſet form of words they may, the words being delivered in a known tongue; By ſet forms we underſtand ſtanding forms, ſuch as come to be uſed again and again, day by day in the ſame words; common ſence ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it evident, men may joyn in prayer, and attend to the Word preached, as well in a new form of words, according to the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which he never heard before, as in a ſet form which he heareth every day.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>But you demand, Is a Miniſter able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the neceſſities of the people, or the doctrine of ſalvation in a form of words deviſed and ſtudied by himſelfe? and is he not able by meditation and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to dictate, and compoſe a Pſalm to be ſung by the people, as occaſion requireth? and if ſo, is not a ſtinted form of ſinging deviſed by men, an arbitrary help to him, and ſo forbidden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Many a good Miniſter that is able to expreſſe the neceſſities of the people, or the doctrine of ſalvation, in a form of words devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſtudied by himſelf: is not able ſo to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate and compoſe a Pſalm to be ſung by the people each ſeveral occaſion, no, though he ſhould meditate and ſtudy hard for it: Poetry is not every good Scholars faculty; nor the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153145:30"/>penning of holy Pſalms the skill of every good Miniſter: nor is it required that it ſhould. For ſeeing the Holy Ghoſt hath already dictated and compoſed to our hands divers forms of Pſalms for all occaſions, it would be ſuperfluous for Miniſters to take up their meditations and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, about the inventing other forms, though they had gifts fit for it: and therefore if ſuch as have the skill to pen Pſalms, do nevertheleſs ſing the forms of Pſalms ſet and compoſed by <hi>David,</hi> and other Prophets: as they cannot be ſaid, therein to make uſe of the inventions of men, but of Gods inſtitutions; ſo neither can they be ſaid to ſin upon the other reſpect, which you mention, becauſe they uſe an help to them not neceſſary; whereas others that want their skill, do lawfully uſe <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms, becauſe ſuch an help to them, is not arbitrary, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: no, no, we do not approve of that diſtinction between arbitrary and neceſſary, in that ſenſe, to that purpoſe; in that ſenſe I ſay, for I here ſee you work upon an equivocation in this word neceſſary; For there is a double neceſſity ſpoken of in this caſe: a ſet form of worſhip may be ſaid to be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, either through ſinfull defects in men, who ſhould be able, but are not, to conceive a form of worſhip of themſelves, or elſe through the nature and condition of the worſhip it ſelfe, which cannot be performed, but in a ſet form, whatſoever the gifts of men be; in this latter ſenſe, not in the former, is the ſinging of Pſalms in a ſet form neceſſary; for unleſſe a Pſalm be expreſſed in a ſet form of words, and ſo ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153145:31"/>the people, all the people cannot joyn in voyce (as well as heart) ſinging and praiſing God together in the ſame words; we admit of no neceſſity of any ſet forms of prayer (or other worſhip) in the former ſenſe: as concerning ſuch men unfit to be Miniſters of the Goſpel as want gifts to conceive a prayer according to the preſent occaſion; but a ſet form of Pſalms we allow as neceſſary in the latter ſenſe, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary (by conſequence) from divine inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for if ſinging of Pſalms be as it is of divine inſtitution: and if Pſalms be a kind of ſpiritual Poetry, and therefore to be put into verſe; If it be alſo of divine inſtitution; that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould joyn as well in voyce, as in heart, in ſinging of Pſalms; and that in a language known, and underſtood by themſelves; then it will be requiſite and neceſſary by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions (for he that inſtituteth the end, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuteth the neceſſary means that leadeth to the end) that in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Churches the Pſalms be tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> verſe, or metre; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Churches in a ſet form; that ſo all the people may joyn with one voyce and heart to praiſe the Lord together in the ſame words, but there is not the like neceſſity of a ſet form of words in prayer: For in prayer (as hath been ſaid) there is no more required of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then when they hear the words of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, to go along with him in heart; and in the end of the prayer to anſwer with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in voyce, <hi>Amen.</hi> And ſo whatſoever is required of the people by divine inſtitution for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153145:31"/>joyning in prayer is fully attained, without a ſet form of words in prayer, which cannot be attained in ſinging without a ſet form of words in Pſalms.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>It is ſaid of prayer, Chriſt hath given gifts to his Miniſters for preaching and praying, hath he not for the ſinging of Pſalms alſo? If it be a diſhonour to Chriſt (as ſome affirme) that they ſhould uſe a form of prayer deviſed by others; Is it not a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour likewiſe, if they ſhall uſe a form of ſinging de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It hath been anſwered above, that though God hath given gifts to his Miniſters for preaching and praying; yet he hath not given to many the gift of inditing Pſalms alſo; and yet neither is it any diſhonour to Chriſt, nor ſinfull defect in his Miniſters that he hath not ſo furniſhed them, ſeeing he himſelf hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently furniſhed them with all ſet forms of Pſalms by the Miniſtry of his Prophets, divinely inſpired for the ſervice of the Church: and it is no diſhonour to Chriſt or his Miniſters that they ſhould take up forms of words deviſed by him for his own worſhip.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>If there be any ſuch neceſſity (of a ſet form of Pſalmes) as is pretended, becauſe ſome Miniſters are not enabled of themſelves to furniſh the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church: It ſhould rather exempt them from the practiſe of ſinging Pſalms, then give li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to a deviſed form; for it is a rule in divinity, that againſt a general negative precept no particular affirmative can be lawfull, unleſſe that particular be warranted in Scripture, &amp;c. But againſt this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153145:32"/>generall negative precept, forbidding all devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed helps, and furtherances in Gods worſhip, there is no particular warrant alowing it in ſinging of Pſalmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not a ſuppoſed, but a reall nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precept that generally forbiddeth all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed helps and furtherances in Gods worſhip, meaning helps and furtherances deviſed by men without warrant from the word: For this is indeed the proper true meaning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement, as hath been ſhewed above: but we deny that ſet forms of Pſalms recorded in Scripture as helps and furtherances deviſed by men, but given by the Holy Ghoſt; and though the tranſlation of the Pſalms both in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and in verſe, be by men, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrant from the Holy Ghoſt, who hath commanded that the Word of God ſhould dwell in us plenteouſly, teaching and admoniſhing one another in Pſalms and Hymnes, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Songs, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. who hath alſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that we ſhould ſing with underſtanding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. which the people could not do to their own underſtanding, or the underſtanding of their brethren, if the Pſalms were not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into their own mother tongue; and when the tranſlation doth fitly expreſſe the ſenſe of the originall Pſalms: we have warrant alſo to make uſe of the tranſlation, though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by ordinary men, as we ſee the Apoſtles did many times make uſe of the tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagints,</hi> provided the tranſlation be not impoſed upon us, as that was not upon
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153145:32"/>and that liberty be ſtill left to correct or reform whatſoever ſhall be found in the tranſlation to ſwerve from the true meaning and juſt weight of the originall Scripture; beſides, it hath been ſhewed above, (in opening the meaning of the ſecond Commandement) that though the negative precept forbid all helps and means of Gods worſhip deviſed by men without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the word: yet not the help of Tongues and Art, which not the wit and will of man, but the wiſdom of God hath provided as neceſſary helps for the furtherance of ſundry parts of Gods worſhip.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures cannot be tranſlated into our Mother Tongue, without the help of Grammer, nor the Pſalms into verſe and metre without the help of Poetry, nor ſung without the help of Muſick (naturall Muſick at the leaſt) and therefore theſe kinds of helps we make uſe of, as not being means of worſhip deviſed, or ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by the wit or will of man, but as they are indeed prepared and ordained (according to the light of nature) by God: And ſo not falling under the generall negative precept which forbiddeth all humane Inventions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions in the worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Now whether the pretended neceſſity of a ſet form, ſhould exempt from the generall negative precept, forbidding deviſed formes, or from the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative precept of ſinging Pſalmes let them judge who put the Exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We doubt not to judge it ſafe to obey the affirmative precept of ſinging Pſalms, in a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153145:33"/>ſet form of words though tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and into verſe by men, becauſe ſet Pſalms are ordained of God, and their tranſlation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh verſe is neceſſarily implyed and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by God himſelf: And yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we do not pretend any neceſſity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt any ſuch ſet form from the generall nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precept which falleth under the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it; for theſe the negative precept did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intend to prohibit: <hi>You need not therefore to wonder</hi> (as you do in the following words) <hi>why ſuch a neceſſity</hi> (as hath been opened) <hi>of a ſet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed form of ſinging ſhould excuſe a ſet form of Pſalms, and yet not excuſe a ſet form of prayer, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſe the people from joyning in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe there is no neceſſity at all of a deviſed ſet form of prayer unleſs it be through the ſinfull defect of the Miniſters gifts in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which is ſuch a neceſſity, as God abhorreth both it and the Miniſter for it; But the neceſſity of a set form of Pſalms is ſuch which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath put, for the Celebration of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with one accord, both in heart and voyce, as hath been ſhewed, and therefore you might well have forborn that confident ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>If Chriſtians ſhall not exempt themſelves from the ſtinted Prayers uſed in the Congregation, untill a materiall difference be ſhewed in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and that diſtinction of Arbitrary, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, deviſed forms be approved by ſolid Reaſons, and holy Scriptures, the world ſhall end</hi> (I am confident) <hi>before they ſhall ſeparate.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:153145:33"/>
               <p>For you ſee a materiall difference in theſe particulars, between the neceſſity of a ſet form of Pſalms, and the neceſſity of a ſet forme of Prayer. The neceſſity of the one is from Gods Ordinance, and therefore warrantable: The neceſſity of the other is from mans Ignorance, and ſuch ignorance as maketh him unfit for the Miniſteriall Office, and therefore ſinfull.</p>
               <p>As for the diſtinction of Arbitrary and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary deviſed forms in your ſence, we neither uſe it nor approve it: And therefore have no cauſe to bring either holy Scriptures or ſolid Reaſons for the proof of it: But in that ſence wherein we uſe it, the diſtinction is ſo manifeſt from what we have ſaid already, that we think your ſelf will require no further proof of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Anſwering to the fourth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>YOur fourth Reaſon may be thus contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, If the Spirit of God do work by means, and if he ſtir up good deſires, yet giveth not ability to expreſſe our deſires, in fit and ſignificant words: Then it is lawfull for us to uſe all godly means to ſtir up the graces of God in us: and to premeditate how to utter our Requeſts, in ſuch a form and manner, as may beſt ſerve for our quickning, and the edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others; and if the uſe of a premeditated form of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153145:34"/>words in prayer do not ſtint the Spirit; a ſet form of Prayer cannot be injurious to the Spirit, grant the one, the other will follow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the ſpeech be of publique prayer, the ſame ſpirit that giveth the Miniſter ability to deliver a Sermon, in fit and ſignificant tearms, doth in like ſort give ability to expreſſe his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in Prayer, in fit and ſignificant tearms: no man is called of God to be a Miniſter of his Church, but he is as well apt to Pray as apt to Preach; But if the ſpeech be of private perſons, it is true, many good ſouls have better deſires than utterance; In regard of which defect or without ſuch defect we willingly condeſcend to you: It is lawfull, yea, and neceſſary to him, to uſe all godly means to ſtir up the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God in him, and to premeditate how to utter his requeſts in ſuch ſort as beſt ſerves for his own quickning, &amp; the edification of others: But this we deny, that the uſing of a preſcript form of Prayer upon a book, deviſed and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by one man upon another to be uſed as their Prayer, is a godly means to ſtir up the graces of God in himſelfe, or to edifie others; For that which the Holy Ghoſt hath not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his Word for the ſtirring up of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God in a mans ſelf or others, that is not a godly means for ſuch an end; But throughout the Scriptures we cannot find any where, that the Holy Ghoſt hath ſanctified ſuch a means to ſuch an end: And then it is but an Image, which will rather teach a form of godlineſſe, than edifie to the power of it.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153145:34"/>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Peradventure they would creep out by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of God is our only helper in the time of Prayer, ſo that though at other times we might uſe helps to ſtir up the graces of the Spirit, yet not in time of prayer: But this diſtinction is not found in Scripture, neither can be deduced by any ſound reaſon from thence. The Spirit of God is at all times the ſole mover, and enabler of us to pray, and the uſe of lawfull means, and ſuch as ſute with the nature of prayer, are at no time unlawfull, as it is fit we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate and read before we pray, ſo it is lawfull in prayer to kneel and lift up our hands and eyes, to uſe the help of the voyce, and the benefit of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian friend to ſtir up affection. Therefore we may diſpute for the lawfullneſſe of book Prayer, thus, if it be lawfull to uſe externall helps in time of prayer, the better to ſtir up affections, then book prayer is not to be condemned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To creep out, being a borrowed ſpeech from worms; It being put upon us hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us forth as worms, and not as men, yea, worſe than worms, (Serpents, rather than Worms:) That being compaſſed in with truth, are willing to creep out by any evaſion, rather than to ſubmit to the authority of the truth: But let our reverend and godly brother, be intreated, not to deal ſuch meaſures to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: Leaſt the God and Father of us both, be diſpleaſed and ſtir up others to returne like meaſure to you, heaped up, preſſed down, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together: our plain and ſimple Anſwer (without creeping or ſhifting) Is this, that it is lawfll to uſe any externall or internall helps,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153145:35"/>either before Prayer, to prepare us for it, or in Prayer to quicken, or inlarge us in it, provided, they be ſuch means and helps as God hath ſanctified to ſuch an end, at ſuch a time.</p>
               <p>As we readily grant the help of books and meditation, before Prayer, ſo we do grant alſo the help of holy and reverent geſtures in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as bowing down the knees, and lifting up of the hands, and eyes, and voyce, the preſence and aſſiſtance of a Chriſtian friend, for all theſe God hath ſanctified, to help the inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the heart in prayer, do but ſhew that God hath ſanctified Book-prayers, impoſed upon us for our prayers, and that by the members of other Congregations, and we will neither creep nor ſtart away: But willingly bleſſe the Lord for his goodneſſe to you in this caſe, (as well as in many others) like as <hi>Phineas</hi> and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> bleſſed God; for the <hi>Rube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> and <hi>Gadites</hi> that were able to give ſo good an account of their actions, beyond the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of their brethren, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>In prayer penned by a godly and well expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Chriſtian, the caſe of a diſtreſſed ſoul may more pithily and amply be deciphered and anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed then he of himſelfe is able to do it; and in ſuch a caſe to deny him this lawfull help, is to take away the Crutch from the lame, and bread from the hungry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In caſe a diſtreſſed ſoul do meet with a prayer penned, by a godly and well experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced Chriſtian, and do find his own caſe, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153145:35"/>and amply deciphered and anatomized therein, we deny not but his heart and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may go along with it, and ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it: And thus far may find it a lawfull help to him; but if you ſet a part ſuch a prayer to ſupport him as a crutch in his prayers (as without which he cannot walk ſtraight and upright in that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) or if he that penned that prayer, or others that have read it, do injoyn it upon him, and forbid him to pray (eſpecially with others) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he uſe that form, this inſtead of a crutch, will prove a cudgell to break the bones of the Spirit in prayer, and force him to halt in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God after the precepts of men; as it hath been ſaid before, ſo it may be again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred here; a man may help his ſpirit in meditation of his mortallity, by behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a dead mans ſcalp, caſt in his way by Gods providence; but if he ſhould ſet a part a deaths head, or take it up as injoyned to him by others, never to meditate or conſerre with others about his mortality, and eſtate of another life, but in the ſight and uſe of the deaths head, ſuch a ſoul ſhall find but a dead heart, and a dead devotion from ſuch a means of mortification; if ſome forms of Prayer, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as gave occaſion to this Diſpute, do now ſeem to be as bread to the hungry, we ſay no more but this, then hungry ſouls will never be ſtarved, that never want ſtore of ſuch like bread as this is.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>The ample and particular laying out of our neceſſities doth eaſe the heart, and move affections,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153145:36"/>and when this may be better done by the help of a Book in prayer then of our ſelves, it is ſenſeleſſe to accuſe the uſe hereof, as a lip-labour, and a quenching of the ſpirit; he ſtinteth not the Spirit that labours to blow the coals of grace, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, he ſtinteth not the Spirit, nor quencheth him; that uſeth any means ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Spirit to blow the coals of grace; but this we deny, that a ſtinted form of prayer upon a book, deviſed by men, and enjoyned to be uſed as the prayers of a Chriſtian ſoul, is a means ſanctified by the Spirit to blow the coals of his grace; or that the repeating of ſuch a ſet form of Prayer, though ample and particular in laying out his neceſſities, will eaſe his heart, or move his affections according to God; God doth not delight ordinarily to breath in the Maſterly injunctions of brethren upon bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or of one Congregation upon another, eſpecially in ſuch things whereof we have neither precept nor preſident in the Word.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>He doth not ſubſtitute his Chriſtian friend, in the place of the word, and Spirit, who not able to lift up his ſoul to God, by reaſon of ſtraightneſſe of heart, and grievous preſſure, doth crave his help and aſſiſtance in prayer, and may not a godly Book ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the want of a Chriſtian companion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is an ordinance of God, to crave the help of the Prayers of our brethren, and to joyn with them; ſhew the like warrant for Prayer upon a book, preſcribed to us, and then we will grant a godly book may ſupply even in this caſe the lacke of a Chriſtian companion;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153145:36"/>If a Miniſter be not able to preach by reaſon of the ſtraightneſſe of his heart, and grievous preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he may get his Chriſtian friend to preach for him; but he may not make uſe of a godly homily enjoyned to him by others, to ſupply the lack of a Chriſtian friend.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Why ſhould it be a ſin to read or pronounce a godly form of Prayer, is it for that it is read and pronounced, or becauſe a man cannot lift up his heart in faith unto God, when he uttereth his requeſts in a ſtinted form of words; to aſſigne the former, is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: To ſay the latter is to offend againſt common experience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not ſay it is a ſin to read or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce a godly form of Prayer; but to read a form of Prayer deviſed by others, and to ſet it a part to read, being deviſed by others enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me as my Prayer; This is ſin, not becauſe it is pronounced, for all publique Prayer is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; nor alwayes in private, becauſe it is read; for (as hath been ſaid) a man may go along in his ſpirit, and be affected with ſome Prayer, which occaſionally he readeth, and may lift up his own heart in it to the Lord; but a ſin it is, as it is ſet apart by himſelfe for his Prayer; or as it is ſo enjoyned to him by others; and in publique it is of ſin, both becauſe it is read, as the Prayer of the Church (and ſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther book brought into the Church beſides Gods Book) And becauſe it is deviſed, not by the gift of Gods Spirit in themſelves, but in others, and alſo becauſe by other it is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed or enjoyned to be read, as the ſervice, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153145:37"/>worſhip of God in another Church: For we do not find that ever God gave warrant either for the offering up of read Prayers to God, as the ordinary prayers of the Church; and leaſt of all for Prayers preſcribed and enjoyned by one Church unto another.</p>
               <p>It is ſo far off from ſuperſtition to affirm this, that we look at it as a ſuperſtition to deny it; for to ſpeak of ſuperſtition according to the true nature of it (and not according to the old Etymologie) If ſuperſtition be <hi>cultus ſupra ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> there is none of all theſe kinds, whether as read upon a book in the Congregation, for their ordinary Prayers; or deviſed by men of other Congregations for that end; or as impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon us by them: but they are all of them, and each one of them, <hi>cultus ſupra ſtatutum,</hi> worſhips and helps, and forms of worſhip which never came into Gods heart to allow for his ſtatute and worſhip.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Will any man object, that read prayer is not Gods Ordinance? It hath been anſwered already, that prayer is the ordinance of God; but whether our prayers be onely conceived in heart, or uttered by words; whether in our own, or other words; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by pronouncing or reading, that is not appointed; when ſpake he one word of prayer within Book or without, in this or that form of words?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Reply hath been made hereto before; as Prayer is an Ordinance of God, ſo are all the lawfull helps and means and forms of Prayer; God hath plainly expreſſed his allowance of Prayer conceived in the heart, and of prayer
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153145:37"/>uttered, and pronounced by words both in our own words, and in the words of others, whom God calleth to be our mouths in the preſent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly: but of ſet forms of read prayer deviſed by men of another Congregation, and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and impoſed upon others; it may juſtly be demanded, when did God ſpeak one word of them? And therefore, what have we to do with them? If it be ſaid as God never ſpake word of reading Prayer within book, ſo never did he ſpeak word of pronouncing Prayer without Book; the Text doth plainly enough expreſſe the contrary; for the Word of God ſpeaketh expreſſely, that Chriſt lift up his eyes to Heaven in Prayer, <hi>John</hi> 17.1. &amp; 11.41. ſo did <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 123.1. and God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed it in the hearts of all his people, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the lifting up of their ſouls, their faith and hope, and deſires to God, by lifting up their eyes ſtedfaſtly to Heaven in Prayer, yea, God hath ingraffed it in the hearts of all men, and even put ſome kind of inſtinct into all living creatures, to lift up their eyes to Heaven for what they want, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.15. Now, if the lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the eyes to Heaven in Prayer be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mentioned in the Word, then how can it be truly ſaid, that God never ſpake word of Prayer without Book? for they that lift up their eyes ſtedfaſtly to Heaven in Prayer, cannot (without ſome diſtractions) caſt them down in Prayer upon a book, if lifting up of the eyes to Heaven in Prayer, be a divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution (as the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ſaid even now) if it be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153145:38"/>an externall means to help the affection of the ſpirit in Prayer) then it is againſt the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and an hinderance to Prayer, inſtead of an help, to ſet a mans ſelf or others, a form of read Prayers, wherein whileſt he is reading he muſt uſually caſt down his eyes upon a Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Tending to give Anſwer unto the fifth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>WHere there is no breach of Law, there is no ſin: But the uſe of a preſcript form of Prayer is no breach of Law, or of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It hath been ſhewed above that it is a breach of the ſecond Commandement more wayes than one, to deviſe and uſe a ſimilitude and form, and means of worſhip, which God never appointed, and ſuch is the reading of a ſer form of Prayer, for the Prayers of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is an uſurpation of more than Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, or Apoſtolicall authority, to preſcribe a ſet form of <hi>Lyturgie,</hi> to the Churches, and a greater uſurpation for one Congregation to preſcribe the ſame to another, which is a ſin both againſt the ſecond and fifth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:153145:38"/>
               <p n="3">3. It is a ſinfull and diſloyall betraying of the ſouls of Magiſtrates to countenance their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding ſuch preſcript forms of Prayer, upon Churches, by taking up the ſame forms from them, which they have not authority from God to injoyne, and ſtifly to plead for them, a ſin forbidden in the fifth and ſixth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a ſinfull betraying of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which Chriſt hath purchaſed to every Church of his by his precious blood: For one Church voluntarily to take up the Injunctions and preſcriptions of another, contrary to <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 22. which argument may be applyed another way, by a Teſtimony from the book of Common-Prayer, Gods Service is perfect Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but the reading of a ſet form of Prayer deviſed, and preſcribed by others is not perfect freedome (for many would be right glad to be freed from it) therefore ſuch reading of prayers is not Gods ſervice.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is a ſinfull breach of the rule of decency, to offer up prayers to God in ſuch a form, as cannot well ſtand with that decent geſture which is moſt ſutable to Prayer, It is a geſture moſt ſutable to Prayer; to lift it up to God as with hearts and hands, ſo with eyes ſtedfaſtly lift up to Heaven: But this geſture cannot fitly, and ſtedfaſtly be uſed, in read Prayer, where the eyes muſt be uſually caſt down upon the Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:153145:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Wherein Anſwer is returned to the ſixth Reaſon.</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>IF a ſet form of prayer be diſallowed, then a preſcript form of Catechiſme and Confeſſion muſt of neceſſity be condemned; but how abſurd this is he is very blind, or will full that ſeeth not, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, antiquity and excellency of catechiſing, is known to them that know any thing, touching the building and governing the Houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Touching ſet forms of Catechiſme, we have anſwered twice before in clearing ſome objections againſt the firſt Reaſon: whereto we refer you, it hath been already ſhewed us, that God himſelfe hath ſet before us ſundry forms of Catechiſme. <hi>Davids</hi> Catechiſme was of one form, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Solomons</hi> of another, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of another, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. Yea, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> name the heads of their Catechiſme, but neither propound the queſtions, nor anſwers them in uſe, An evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Argument they never meant to bind Churches to ſet forms of Catechiſme: The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and neceſſary uſe of catechizing young men, and novices (as hath been ſaid before) we willingly acknowledge: But little benefit have we ſeen reaped from ſet forms of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153145:39"/>and anſwers deviſed by one Church, and impoſed by neceſſity upon another: They muſt look at them with coloured Spectacles, that can diſcern them: The like may be ſaid of forms of Confeſſions, when a Church is ſuſpected and ſlandered with corrupt and unſound Doctrine, they have a call from God, to ſet forth a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique confeſſion of their faith. But to preſcribe the ſame as the confeſſion of the faith of that Church to their poſterity, or to preſcribe the confeſſion of one Church to be a form, and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern unto others, ſad experience hath ſhewed what a ſnare it hath been to both, nothing in after ages muſt be held for a doctrine of the Church (though never ſo neceſſary a truth) unleſſe it were found amongſt the Articles of Religion agreed upon by their fathers, in the confeſſion of their Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:153145:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Giving Anſwer to the ſeaventh Reaſon.</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>IT is lawfull to aske common bleſſings of God dayly in a ſet form of words,</hi> Ergo. <hi>It is not unlawfull to uſe a ſet form of Prayer; and if to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it, to read it alſo: for reading of it ſelfe, is not impure, as pronouncing cannot make an evill matter good, no more can reading make a good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evill, pronouncing and reading being Adjuncts in prayer both indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> with us is not ſo much about ſet forms of prayer in generall, as about ſet forms of Prayer deviſed by men of other Churches, precſribed, and injoyned to be read as the Prayers of the Church, or deviſed by one Chriſtian, and ſet apart by another, as his prayers, to which this Argument reacheth not.</p>
               <p>Though we do not deny it to be altogether unlawfull to ſeek common bleſſings of God dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a ſet form of words, yet we would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men to reſt and content themſelves in ſo doing, much leſſe to bind themſelves ſo to do: For beſides that, a daily ſet form will eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate to a formallity, how can a Chriſtian be ſaid to watch unto prayer (which we are
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153145:40"/>commanded to do, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18.) If we content our ſelves with the ſame ſet form of prayer, this year, as the laſt: Beſides, the common daily bleſſings, which the <hi>Diſcourſer</hi> inſtanceth in; as faith, patience, meekneſſe, love, ſanctification of Gods name. Coming of Chriſts Kingdome, the ſtate of theſe things doth ever and anon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to bind a mans ſelfe daily to a ſet form of prayer, for ſuch things as the ſtate whereof is ſo daily varied, will bring in a looſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous kind of prayers, fit only for thoſe, that do not diſcern, or are not affected with the preſent ſtate of things, either in themſelves, or others.</p>
               <p>When it is ſaid, if it be lawfull to pronounce a ſet form of prayer, then to read it; If the meaning be to read it, for a prayer, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is not firm, for though (as the <hi>Diſcourſer</hi> ſaith) the reading of prayer is not impure: Yet the praying of read prayers is the uſing of ſuch a Crutch to pray (as he ſpeaketh) which God hath not appointed, and that maketh ſuch read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impure: And though pronouncing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make an evill matter good, nor ſimply read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing make a good matter evill, yet reading to ſuch an end, reading a ſet form of prayer, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to me for my prayer, maketh to me a Will-worſhip of that which he that concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the prayer might lawfully have pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>The pronouncing of a good Sermon by him that made it, is a good and acceptable ſervice to God, and his Church: But to read a Sermon
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153145:41"/>as my preaching, which was made by another, maketh it neither ſo acceptable to God, nor to his Church, yea the reading of a mans own Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon inſtead of preaching will much detract from the life and power of it, and make a man of God unſerviceable for his place: Though reading and pronouncing of a thing, be both of them adjuncts, and common adjuncts too, to that which is pronounced or read, yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ends and ſubjects, to which they may be applyed, the one may be lawfull, the other not indifferent but ſinfull, the reading of a Sermon for preaching, is a ſinfull manner of preaching; The difference will ever hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the word read, and preached: They are two diſtinct Ordinances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Anſwering unto the eight Reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Jewes before the coming of Chriſt uſed a preſcript form of Prayer</hi> (as it is probable, and the learned note) <hi>in the celebration of the Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and that which they uſed</hi> (as is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) <hi>was approved by Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the <hi>Jewes</hi> before the coming of Chriſt, did uſe certain Rites in keeping the Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, It doth appear by the Teſtimonies alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153145:41"/>as alſo by <hi>Cauſabon,</hi> and others: And that ſome forms of Prayer they uſed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the ſeverall paſſages of the Paſſeover required: But it doth not at all appear that they uſed any ſet forms of Prayer, but onely to that and the like effect, and that not by Preſcript or Injunction from one to another, but leaving every father of a family at his liberty therein, much leſſe will it appear that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, took up any ſet forms of Prayer by their example and leaſt of all from their Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Giving Anſwer to the ninth Reaſon</head>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>ALL the reformed Churches at this day, do not only tollerate, but approve a ſet form of Liturgie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We count it a ſafe courſe to bewail our own ſins and the ſins of our fathers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we have polluted the holy things of God, more or leſſe, rather than to juſtifie our own alterations from the rule by their preſidents; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat cauſe we have to bleſſe the Lord for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat light which the inſtruments whom God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed in reforming all Proteſtant Churches
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153145:42"/>brought into the dark world, and left behind them: and yet it is well known in ſome thing or other, all of them, more or leſſe failed: and it is more wonder they ſhould ſee ſo much truth out of the midſt of darkneſſe, then that they who ſaw ſo much, ſhould fail in any thing but whereinſoever they failed the generation that have come after them, have too cloſely and ungodly ſtuck to their examples, yea, and have been more zealous in the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, than have ſought to perfect what they leſs defective; yet this we may truly affirm, that we know none of all the reformed forraign Churches that do preſcribe a ſet form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with neceſſity to be obſerved; but leave their Miniſter at liberty to uſe the ſame, or ſome other form to the like effect at their own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which taketh off a great part of ſin, and burthen of ſet forms; God knoweth how to paſſe by the remnant of iniquity of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of them that ſeek him in truth, although all the high places be not taken away, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 15.17. The Lord did not ſo look at their high places, as to reject his people for Idolaters or Superſtitious Perſons, when they ſought him in (truth of heart) though in high places; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet would he juſtifie their high places to after Ages, by the example and authority of their Anceſtors: farre be it from us to cenſure the preſent Churches of obſtinacy, who have perſiſted in the preſidents left by our holy ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, thoſe firſt reformed; yet neither may we be ſo unfaithfull as to ſowe Pillowes under
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153145:42"/>the Elbows, no, not of publique Churches, who knoweth not they have all been more ſtudious and tenacious of what form the doctrine and worſhip, and diſcipline was left unto them, then inquiſitive after farther light, yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more inclinable to look back into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> than to haſten towards <hi>Canaan;</hi> it is true, we have cauſe to ſuſpect our ſelves of error, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſo many glorious lights of former and preſent times (to wit) if our faith were built upon our ſelves, we ſhould prefer their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and teſtimony before our own; but ſeeing our faith reſteth only on the word of the Lord, and his Spirit breathing therein, and the Word hath promiſed more and more light ſhall break forth in theſe times, till <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> be utterly conſumed and aboliſhed; we ſhall ſin againſt the Grace and Word of truth if we confine our truth, either to the Divines of preſent or former ages.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Be that all the Churches may erre in this, yet I hope no moderate man can cenſure them of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, as men not willing to conſent to the truth ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and manifeſted; how then cometh it to paſſe, that none of them hitherto have ſubſcribed to this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the practice of our brethren of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration? The true Churches of God cannot erre fundamentally, nor obſtinately againſt knowledge; but how can they be freed from one of theſe, let the oppoſites themſelves judge.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:153145:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though we do not believe (as you do) that the true Churches of Chriſt cannot erre fundamentally, but doe conceive for a time they may (as the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the golden Calfe, and afterwards more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly in the crucifying of Chriſt, and many Chriſtian Churches almoſt all, in that time, when <hi>Hierome</hi> complaineth the whole world was become an <hi>Arian</hi>) yet we do not look at the reading of deviſed preſcript forms, as a fundamentall error: howbeit any error or ſin perſiſted in againſt light, will in time argue an unſound and corrupt heart in the bottom. And although we dare not excuſe true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (as you do) from poſſibility of obſtinacy, at leaſt in ſome degree (for we ſee <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets often taxing the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of rebellion and obſtinacy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.27. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.7.) yet we dare not think that the Churches of Chriſt do ſin of obſtinacy (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of reigning obſtinacy) in this caſe; For many of them never ſaw the grounds, as have born witneſſe againſt ſet and preſcript read forms of Prayer; and thoſe that have ſeen their grounds, have not been convinced of the ſolidity of them; and therefore may not be charged with obſtinacy, till after they have been convict of ſinne herein, and yet perſiſt herein againſt light of conſcience, which God forbid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Reaſon (from the judgement and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of other Churches) hath been wont to be of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153145:43"/>great force in former times; otherwiſe the Apoſtle would never have alledged the practiſe and conſent of the Churches to confirm the faithfull, and to ſtop the mouths of the contentious,</hi> Acts 15.22.28. 1 Cor. 11.16. and 14.34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Argument from the practice and judgement of Churches, was of greater force in the Apoſtles time than ever ſince: the eſtate of the Churches as then remained <hi>tanquam intemerata virgo,</hi> whileſt the Apoſtles and the Apoſtolique men lived; men that could not erre themſelves; and were more watchfull and zealous than to ſuffer any error to get head in any of the Churches; but let them that preſs the like argument now, let them ſhew us the like infallibillity, vigilancy and zeal, of the guides of the Churches in theſe dayes; and we ſhall readily captivate our own judgements to ſuch divine teſtimony: otherwiſe the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Churches now, being but humane te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony (unleſſe it might appear grounded in Scripture warrant) we only hearken thus far to an Argument taken from the Churches, as reverently and meekly to attend to it, and if it diſſent from Scripture, yet ſtill to bear with meekneſſe and patience, and brotherly love, any failing which is found in them; but not therefore to approve and juſtifie all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153145:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Touching the other Queſtion of the peoples joyning in prayer with the reading of a deviſed preſcript Liturgie.</head>
               <p>FInally, your Diſcourſe cometh along to make good a third aſſertion, which you had at firſt made a part of the ſtate of the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit,</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>That though it were unlawfull for the Miniſters to uſe a preſcript form of prayer; yet no reaſon can be ſhewed, why it ſhould be unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the people to be preſent at ſuch prayers and aſſemblies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We conceive that good reaſon may be ſhewed. Why, if it be unlawfull for the Miniſter to pray upon a book, a deviſed and preſcript form of prayer: it is unlawfull like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the people ſo to be preſent at it, as to joyn with it, or ſeem to joyn with it.</p>
               <p>Our firſt reaſon is taken from the unity of the Church, if the Officers or Miniſters, and all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153145:44"/>the members of the Church be one body, (as they are ſaid to be, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.) the ſinne of the Miniſter of the Church openly committed in the publique worſhip of God, is the ſin of them all that do joyne with him, and do not bear witneſſe againſt his ſinne according to God.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Reaſon may be taken from the compactneſſe of Gods worſhip, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which all the members in the Church have in it; all the worſhip of God in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, is put up to God, as well by the people as by the Miniſters <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with one accord, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.14. The Prayer of the Miniſter is the Prayer of them; the matter of his prayer is the matter of all their prayers; the form of his prayer (I ſpeak of the externall form, which is that wherein they can joyn) is the form of them; if then it be unlawfull for the Miniſter to pray upon a book, a deviſed preſcript form of prayer: it is alike unlawfull for the people to joyn with him.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>The people are commanded to examine themſelves before they draw nigh unto the preſence of God, but not to examine whether the Miniſters pray in one form or other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The members of the Church are not indeed to examine the ſecret ſins of any but themſelves, but the open ſins of any of their brethren, they ought to admoniſh one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153145:45"/>thereof, and to prevent with holy watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe the ſinnes of one another, elſe the ſin of one <hi>Achan</hi> becometh the ſin and plague of all <hi>Iſrael, Joſhua</hi> 7.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>If the Miniſter pray coldly, (as they ſay all reading of ſtinted forms maketh but cold prayer: a drawing nigh to God with the lips; when the heart is far from him) yet this is the fault of the Miniſter only, not of all that are preſent, for ſuch may be the Miniſters fault to pray coldly, even in a conceived forme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, We do not ſay (for our parts) that all praying upon a book or inſtituted forms, is but cold prayer, becauſe God may pardon the ignorance of his people, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſincerity of their hearts, help them with ſome ſpirituall affections, even in ſuch prayers, howbeit, a form of prayer not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God will not (of it ſelf) affect the heart with heavenly warmth, neither do we ſay that the coldneſſe of the Miniſters heart in prayer, if it ſpring from the inward corruption of his own ſpirit, doth wrap the people into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the ſame ſinne, <hi>de ſecretis non Judicat Eccleſia,</hi> nor is it defiled by the tolleration of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins in others.</p>
               <p>But if the people be convinced, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of prayer upon a book preſcribed to them by man, is a ſin againſt the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo no true help or means of Gods
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153145:45"/>worſhip, is therefore ſome hinderance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to it, then the people ſhall be guilty, not only of the fellowſhip of thoſe forms of Prayer, but alſo of the coldneſs of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters heart therein, if they willingly joyn in that which corrupteth and cooleth his ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Coldneſſe and lip-labour in prayer is not helped with Separation, but by joyning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections of the heart with the outward Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, if the coldneſſe ſpring onely from the corruption of the Miniſters heart, and not from the unſanctified means and helpleſſe help of Prayer which he uſeth, to wit, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript form of book-prayer; but as no man can waſh his hands from ſin, that removeth not away all outward occaſions of ſuch ſin, as much as in him lyeth, from himſelf and others, ſo no man can be freed from the guilt of ſuch cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the Miniſter and the people do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract by the cuſtomary uſe of ſuch deviſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript forms of Prayer, if he do not ſo much as in him lyeth remove ſuch occaſions of evil from them.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>The Jewes uſed a ſtinted form of prayer (or Liturgie) in the Synagogues, at the celebration of the Paſſeover, before the dayes of our Saviour Chriſt; yet Chriſt never perſwaded the people to abſent themſelves, nor did he withdraw himſelf, but
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153145:46"/>reſorted to their Synagogues, and the Temple; as did alſo his Apoſtles after his aſcenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Of the Jewiſh forms of Prayer, we have ſpoken before, And have juſtly denied that they took up any book prayers, deviſed by others preſcribed to them; and therefore no marvell if neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themſelves from them; ſeeing the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward face of adminiſtrations, was only of Gods Ordinances, not of the inventions of men, at the leaſt ſo farre as not to draw them into fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip or communion with them therein; the corruptions ſound amongſt them, both in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and worſhip Chriſt and his Apoſtles did freely bear witneſſe againſt, both to themſelves, and the people.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>It is not lawfull to ſeparate from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or aſſemblies of the Saints, in whoſe fellowſhip we may ſerve God with an holy worſhip, and believe in him with an holy faith; for if a prayer conceived in the heart and uttered with the voice be a pure ſervice of God, the ſame read upon a book, becometh not impure to them that hear it with holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not ſeparate from the Church and aſſembly of the Saints, but willingly joyn with you in every part of your holy worſhip; and in every doctrine of your holy faith only we withdraw our ſelves from ſuch parts of your adminiſtrations, wherein we cannot
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153145:46"/>joyn with you, but wrap our ſelves into the fellowſhip of ſuch ſin which (in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) we ſee committed by you: How the ſame Prayer conceived by the ſpirit of a Miniſter, and pronounced in his own, and in the peoples name to God, may be a pure ſervice to God, yet the ſame written in a book, and preſcribed to others to be read by them as their Prayers, may be an unlawfull form of worſhip hath been ſhewed above; it is weariſome to repeat the ſame things ſo often.</p>
               <p>Diſc. <hi>Laſtly, The Scribes and the Phariſees ſinned grievouſly in corrupting the Law with their falſe gloſſes, and defiling the worſhip of God with their own inventions; nevertheleſſe, the faithfull held fellowſhip and communion with them in the worſhip of God; and that by the approbation of the Prophets, and of Chriſt himſelf; but ſurely the health of the Church is more crazed by ſuch great infirmities, than by the onely toleration and uſe of a preſcript form of prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſubſtance of this objection hath been anſwered even now; the faithfull did, and might lawfully joyn in worſhiping God in his own Ordinances, notwithſtanding the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall pollution which the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees brought in, both in doctrine and worſhip; for corruptions in doctrine do not draw the hearers into fellowſhip of the ſame faith: if they beware of the leaven of ſuch doctrine, and bear witneſſe againſt it; in time and place according
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153145:47"/>to God; &amp; as for the pollutions in worſhip, they chiefly lay in their private ſuperſtitious devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of waſhing their hands, and pots, and cups, and brazen veſſels, and not in their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtrations of publique Ordinances; eſpecially in ſuch wherein their act and the peoples was offered up together with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; but there is not the like reaſon of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Prayer, wherein both Miniſter and people do all joyn together, as one man, with one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; where any known ſin in the outward adminiſtration of the Miniſter is the ſin of all the people that joyn with him. The Lord give us hearts to deny our ſelves, and to ſit cloſe to him; that he may delight to lead us on by his ſpirit of truth, in all truth and goodneſſe; and ſtill delight to be mercifull to us, in pardoning and healing all our forms and preſent polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for his holy Names ſake in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:48"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153145:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
